<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two treatises: I. The saints communion with Jesus Christ, sacramental, spiritual, and celestial; wherein ministers and Christian are excited to a conscientious administration, and participation of that, of late-time, in many places, too much neglected ordinance, the sacrament of the Lords Supper; wherein that great controversie of a free admission is debated. II. Acquaintance with God; the nature of it opened, the practice perswaded, encouraged, directed, cautioned. / As it was lately delivered to the Church of God at Great Yarmouth, by John Brinsley, minister of the Gospel there.</title>
            <author>Brinsley, John, 1600-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 216 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 119 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77514</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4735</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1547_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209457</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868339</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868339</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170076</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77514)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170076)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 196:E1547[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two treatises: I. The saints communion with Jesus Christ, sacramental, spiritual, and celestial; wherein ministers and Christian are excited to a conscientious administration, and participation of that, of late-time, in many places, too much neglected ordinance, the sacrament of the Lords Supper; wherein that great controversie of a free admission is debated. II. Acquaintance with God; the nature of it opened, the practice perswaded, encouraged, directed, cautioned. / As it was lately delivered to the Church of God at Great Yarmouth, by John Brinsley, minister of the Gospel there.</title>
                  <author>Brinsley, John, 1600-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30], 207, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Newberry, at the Three Lyons in Cornhil, near the Royal Exchange.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654. [i.e. 1653]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The saints communion with Jesus Christ" and "Acquaintance with God" have separate dated title pages; register and pagination and continuous.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "4. Octob. 1653"; the 4 in the imprint date has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew XXVI, 29 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Job XXII, 21 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>God --  Worship and love --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170076:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO TREATISES: I. The Saints Communion with Jeſus Chriſt, Sacramental, Spiritual, and Celeſtial; wherein Miniſters and Chriſtians are excited to a Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Adminiſtration, and Partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of that, of late time, in many places, too much neglected Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, the Sacrament of the Lords Supper; wherein that great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie of a free Admiſſion is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated. II. Acquaintance with God; the nature of it opened, the practice perſwaded, encouraged, directed, cautioned. As it was lately delivered to the Church of God at Great <hi>Yarmouth,</hi> By <hi>John Brinſley,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Newberry,</hi> at the Three Lyons in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> near the Royal Exchange. 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:170076:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170076:2"/>
            <p>REader, pardoning thoſe (too many) miſpointings, which (ſpecially in the former of theſe <hi>Treatiſes</hi>) hath ſometimes rendered the ſenſe perplexed, be pleaſed to correct theſe literal and verbal miſtakes of the Preſs.</p>
            <p>ERRATA.</p>
            <p>PAg. 11. line 21. read thoſe, p. 19. l. 23. r. his own, p. 23. l. 23. r. prophecy, p. 28. l. laſt, r. intimation, p. 29. l. 12. r. Sun of Righteouſneſs, p. 33. l. 5. r. thoſe, p. 34. l. 5. r. as comfortable a way, p. 39. l. 11. r. drink, p. 47. l. 18. r. third, p. 50. l. 10. r. promiſed, p. 52. l. 17. r. preſidency, p. 57. l. 1. r. not for, p. 79. l. 23. r. ye, p. 88. l. 14. r. to ſtrengthen him againſt, p. 90. l. 13. r. ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, p. 95. l. 21. r. be they, p. 128. l. 17. r. pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos, p. 160. marg. r. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170076:3"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:170076:3"/>
                  <p>THE Saints Communion WITH JESUS CHRIST, Sacramental, Spiritual, and Celeſtial. Wherein Miniſters and Chriſtians are excited to a Conſcientious Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration and Participation of that, of late time, in many places, too much neglected Ordinance, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lords Supper. As it was lately delivered to the Church of God at Great <hi>Yarmouth,</hi> By <hi>John Brinſley,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel there.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Newberry</hi> at the Three Lyons in Cornhil, near the Royal Exchange. 1654.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170076:4"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:170076:4"/>
                  <head>To the Reverend, and my much honored Fathers, and Brethren, the Miniſters of the Goſpel in the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who deſire to be found faithful. <hi>Grace, Mercy, and Peace.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>(Reverend, and much honored in the Lord)</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Ardon the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of this <hi>Dedicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> which hath faln to you, not more by <hi>choice,</hi> then <hi>neceſsity.</hi> In this enſuing
<pb facs="tcp:170076:5"/>
                     <hi>Tract,</hi> (as the <hi>Text</hi> offered, and the exigency of the times required it,) I have taken occaſion, once and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, to excite Chriſtians to a conſciencious attendance upon that ſacred <hi>Ordinance,</hi> the <hi>Sacrament of the Supper,</hi> as being both a <hi>ſign</hi> and a <hi>ſeal,</hi> a <hi>repreſentation</hi> and a <hi>pledge</hi> of that bleſſed <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion,</hi> which they hope to have another day with <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and one with another in the <hi>Kingdom of their Father.</hi> Now ſo it is, that in the way of this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, (at the requeſt of ſome now walking abroad) I foreſee a double <hi>rub,</hi> which without your help I am not
<pb facs="tcp:170076:5"/>able to remove. The one is, the late <hi>diſuſe of this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> in ſome places; the other, the <hi>promiſcuous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution</hi> of it in others. The former of which deprives many of this <hi>Sacramental Communion,</hi> who are deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of it, and in meaſure fitted for it. The latter diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courageth ſome others, who out of tenderneſs of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience dare not communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate; where they conceive (though without any juſt ground) their bare preſence may make them acceſſory to ſuch a profanation. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this double account it is, that I now make this <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatory addreſs</hi> to you; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb facs="tcp:170076:6"/>the ſum of my <hi>requeſt</hi> is, That ſo many of you as are intereſted in the (ſuppoſed) guilt of either of theſe, would be pleaſed ſeriouſly and ſpeedily to apply your ſelves (ſo much as in you is) to the redreſs thereof. A ſad thing it is, which the <hi>Church</hi> complains of in a litteral ſenſe, <hi>Lam.</hi> 4.4. <hi>That children ſhould cry for bread, and that there ſhould be none to break it to them.</hi> And it is no leſs, that the <hi>children of the Kingdom</hi> ſhould cry for <hi>Sacramental Bread,</hi> and that there ſhall be none to <hi>break it</hi> unto them; none to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter this Ordinance to them, to which they have
<pb facs="tcp:170076:6"/>as good right, as to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Pardon me here, if I take the boldneſs to minde you of what I know you cannot but remember, and will be ready to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that you are not <hi>Lords,</hi> but <hi>Stewards of the myſteries of God.</hi> Now (as the great <hi>Apoſtle</hi> maketh the <hi>Application</hi> of this <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> 1 Cor. 4.1, 2.) <hi>It is required in ſtewards, that a man be found faithful.</hi> Many other <hi>qualifications</hi> there are requiſite in ſuch an <hi>offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer;</hi> but none more, none ſo much as this of <hi>fidelity.</hi> And wherein doth that conſiſt, but in a free diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution of what is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:170076:7"/>to him according to his maſters will for the good of the family, <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to every one his por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in due ſeaſon?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luke 12.46.</note> And this it is which I do here hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beg from all of you, that you would in ſuch a way approve your ſelves faithful to God, and his people, by a free diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all <hi>Ordinances,</hi> which he hath betruſted you with. This ſome, and many of you have done, and do, in the diſpenſing of the <hi>Word;</hi> and why not alſo the <hi>Sacraments.</hi> Surely, theſe are to be looked upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe ſacred <hi>Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries;</hi> by which name they
<pb facs="tcp:170076:7"/>were known to ſome of the <hi>Ancients,</hi> who were wont to call the <hi>Euchariſtical Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Dreadful Myſteries.</hi> And as ſure I am, that the due <hi>adminiſtration</hi> of them is within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs of your <hi>Commiſsion:</hi> As of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> ſo of the <hi>Supper;</hi> which our Saviour in the firſt Inſtitution held forth to his Apoſtles with an <hi>Hoc facite, Do this;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.24, 25.</note> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting them, (as it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived) what they (and all the <hi>Miniſters of the Goſpel</hi> in ſucceeding ages, there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented by them) were at that time to do in <hi>participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> and afterwards in <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing</hi> of that <hi>Ordinance,
<pb facs="tcp:170076:8"/>viz.</hi> To imitate his example in <hi>taking, bleſsing, eating, drinking</hi> the <hi>Sacramental Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine, giving</hi> both to the people in comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration of his <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Paſsion.</hi> This, in obedience to his command, they after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards accordingly did. Let not any of their <hi>Succeſſors</hi> then lay aſide this <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</hi> nor yet without un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable neceſſity ſuſpend it. Our bleſſed <hi>Saviour,</hi> knowing his departure to be at hand, how deſirous was he to celebrate the <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal,</hi> and <hi>Euchariſtical Supper</hi> with his. Apoſtles? <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>With deſire</hi> (ſaith he to them) <hi>I have deſired to eat
<pb facs="tcp:170076:8"/>this Paſsover with you, before I ſuffer.</hi> Luk. 22.15. And let the like motive prevail with you, not knowing how nigh the time of your departure may be, not to put off from <hi>moneth</hi> to <hi>moneth,</hi> from <hi>year</hi> to <hi>year</hi> (as in too many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of late times hath been done) the celebration of this <hi>Ordinance:</hi> In which neglect, as the <hi>Ordinance</hi> ſuffers not a little, ſo the Church much, and that more ways then one.</p>
                  <p>And as for you (my <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi>) who do hold forth this <hi>Ordinance,</hi> let me (in the name of your <hi>Maſter</hi> and mine) beg it at your hands, that you would endeavor to
<pb facs="tcp:170076:9"/>diſpenſe it in ſuch a way, as thoſe who have moſt right unto it, may not be diſheart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from partaking in it. <hi>Caſt ye up, caſt ye up, prepare the way, take up the ſtumbling block out of the way of my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;</hi> ſo runs the <hi>Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Iſai.</hi> 57.14. Which let it ſo far take place with you, as that you may not by any act of yours obſtruct, or (ſo much as in you lieth to remedy it) ſuffer to be obſtructed the way to the Lords Table, whereby any of his people ſhould be hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred from having <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental communion</hi> with him. Amongſt which <hi>obſtructions</hi> I know none at the preſent
<pb facs="tcp:170076:9"/>more obvious, then that which I have pointed at, of promiſcuous and <hi>mixt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munions,</hi> the admitting of all ſorts to this Sacrament. Which, however happily it be not ſo juſt a ground of ſtumbling to others, as they may make it, yet in it ſelf it cannot be denied to be an abuſe, and <hi>profanation</hi> of that <hi>Ordinance.</hi> So it was looked upon in the laſt age, and that by ſuch as were free from the imputation of (ſince ſo called) <hi>Purita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm.</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Si quem indignum eſſe palam conſtiterit, is ad coenam â pastore minimè eſt admitten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus, quià ſine Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti id profanatione fieri non poteſt.</hi> Nowelli <hi>Catech. in quarto, pro pè ad fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem; Im pr. Anno</hi> 1570.</note> 
                     <hi>If any be openly known to be unworthy, the Paſtor ought not to admit him to the Supper, becauſe it cannot be done without profane abuſe of
<pb facs="tcp:170076:10"/>the Sacrament;</hi> As that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Dean of <hi>Pauls,</hi> Dr. <hi>Nowel</hi> in his approved, and then <hi>Authorized Catechiſm</hi> hath reſolved it. And it is no other <hi>doctrine,</hi> then what the <hi>Church</hi> then held forth in her <hi>Rubrick before the Communion;</hi> where ſhe not onely allows, but enjoyns her Miniſters not to <hi>admit perſons ſcandalous, or malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the Lords Table.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Not ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the Lords Table, &amp;c.] <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick before the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</hi>
                     </note> Let not this Direction and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction then be ſlighted by any of you, who account it your Honor to be called the <hi>Sons</hi> of that <hi>Mother:</hi> But looking upon this, not onely as your <hi>liberty,</hi> but your <hi>duty,</hi> ſee that with holy
<pb facs="tcp:170076:10"/>care and conſcience you ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply your ſelves to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of it. It is that which the <hi>Lord</hi> telleth his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Jeremy,</hi> (being then in a diſtracted condition in regard of the preſent times, and not knowing well how to demean himſelf in the execution of his office in the midſt of ſo many diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements as he then met with,) <hi>If thou take forth the precious from the vile, thou ſhalt be as my mouth. Jer.</hi> 15.19. This would he have him do in his teaching, to put a difference betwixt the good and the bad, Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Goſpel</hi> to the one, and <hi>Law</hi> to the other; confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:170076:11"/>and comforting the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, ſharply reproving and menacing of the latter. And ſo doing, the Lord tells him he ſhould be <hi>his mouth,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove himſelf a true and faithful Miniſter of his. And what is there ſaid of that part of the <hi>Miniſterial Office,</hi> not unfitly may it be applied to this, the diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of this <hi>Sacrament.</hi> If herein you ſhall <hi>ſeparate the precious from the vile,</hi> put a difference betwixt thoſe who (as to <hi>Man</hi>) are <hi>worthy</hi> and <hi>unworthy,</hi> reaching forth this Ordinance to all, and onely ſuch, as in the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a well-regulated <hi>Charity</hi> may be looked upon
<pb facs="tcp:170076:11"/>as meet gueſts for that Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, now ſhall ye be as <hi>Gods hand,</hi> owned by him in this your Miniſtration.</p>
                  <p>Thus have I briefly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented my deſires to both of you. To which, what <hi>anſwer</hi> I am like to receive at ſome hands, I cannot but foreſee; and therefore give me leave to meet it with a ſhort <hi>Replication.</hi> True it is, the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Ordinance, and that in ſuch a way, it muſt be acknowledged to be the Miniſters duty; but how ſhall it in theſe times be diſcharged by him? What, ſhall every <hi>Paſtor</hi> then aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume and exerciſe a <hi>ſole
<pb facs="tcp:170076:12"/>power and juriſdiction</hi> over his flock, to admit and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe as it pleaſeth him? To this I will not, I dare not, ſay <hi>Amen.</hi> That which <hi>Prelacy</hi> hath diſclaimed, let not ordinary <hi>Paſtors</hi> make challenge to. <hi>What remedy then</hi> (it will be ſaid) <hi>is to be found, and uſed for this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief of mixt communions?</hi> To this I ſhall deſire an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer may be received from that forecited Author, which I preſume may finde better acceptance from his hand,
<note place="margin">Magiſt. <hi>Quod ergo remedium huic malo invenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſt, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que adbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendum?</hi>
                     </note> then mine.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Churches wel-ordered and wel-managed</hi> (I ſhall give it you in his own words, as I finde them
<pb facs="tcp:170076:12"/>tranſlated) <hi>there was ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and kept a certain Form and Order of Governance.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Audit. <hi>In Eccleſiis benè inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutis atque moratis, certa ut</hi> [Pag. 92. Matth. 18.15, 16, 17. Acts 14.23 &amp; 15.4, 6. d. 22.24.20. d. 17. f. 28. 1 Cor. 6.2.1, 2. &amp; 12. d. 28. &amp; 14. c. 26. g. 40. 1 Tim. 5. c. 17. Tit. 1. b. 5.] <hi>anteà dixi, ratio atque ordo guber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nationis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituebatur atque obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vabatur. Deligeban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Seuio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, id eſt Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtici, qui Diſciplinam Eccleſiaſticam tenerent at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que colerent: Ad hos authoritas, animadverſio, atque caſtigatio cenſoria pertinebant:</hi> [1 Cor. 5. a. 1.4.5. &amp; 11. c. 16. d. 18, &amp;c.] <hi>Hi adhibito etiam Paſtore, ſi quos eſſe cognoverant, qui vel opinionibus falſis, vel turbulentis erroribus, vel anilibus ſuperſtitionibus, vel vitâ vitiosâ flagitiosâqve magnam publicè offenſionem Eccleſiae Dei adferrent, quique ſine coenae Dominicae profanatione accedere non poſſent, cos a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Communione repellebant, atque rejiciebant, neque rurſum admitte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, donec poenitentiâ publicâ Eccleſia ſatisfeciſſent.</hi> Nowelli Catech. ubi ſupra.</note> 
                     <hi>There were choſen Elders, that is, Eccleſiaſtical Magiſtrates, to hold and keep the Diſcipline of the Church. To theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed the Authority, looking to, and Correction, like Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors. Theſe calling to them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the Paſtor, if they knew any that either with falſe opinions, or troubleſome errors, or vain ſuperſtitions, or with corrupt and wicked life brought pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly any great offence to the Church of God, and which might not come without pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faning the Lords Supper, did put back ſuch from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and rejected them,
<pb facs="tcp:170076:13"/>and did not admit them again, till they had with publick pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance ſatisfied the Church.]</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This was the beſt, and onely ſolution, which that judicious and <hi>authorized Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſt</hi> in the laſt age was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to hold forth. And tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for my part, I muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that (ſeeing the late Reverend Aſſembly could
<pb facs="tcp:170076:13"/>not) I do deſpair of finding out a better. All the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining ſcruple then will be, what ſhall be done in thoſe places where ſuch aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtants are not to be found? In the reſolving whereof, I ſhall humbly crave your help; onely taking the boldneſs to leave this moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with you. That where a <hi>Juridical</hi> cannot be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, you would rather chooſe to act in a <hi>Precarious,</hi> and <hi>Paſtoral way,</hi> then to ſuffer ſo great and uſeful an Ordinance to be laid aſide, as of late times in too many places it hath been.</p>
                  <p>More I have not, ſave onely to <hi>apologize</hi> for one
<pb facs="tcp:170076:14"/>other Branch of the <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe,</hi> wherein I have freely declared my apprehenſions concerning the <hi>geſture,</hi> which is in this Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion uſed, <hi>viz.</hi> Of <hi>ſitting at the Table in the act of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</hi> This I have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, and muſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, as conceiving it moſt agreeable to the firſt <hi>pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern,</hi> and to the ſubſequent practiſe of the <hi>Proto-primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Churches</hi> in the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical times, as alſo ſuiting beſt with the nature of the duty; and conſequently freeſt from all juſt excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. But not with any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to cenſure all other different forms of admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration;
<pb facs="tcp:170076:14"/>as well knowing, that all places of publick meeting cannot with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency admit of this. Which having preſented unto you, I ſhall now leave you, where I found you, under the gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection and guidance of him, who <hi>holdeth the ſeven Stars in his right hand, and walketh in the midſt of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven golden Candleſticks:</hi> Humbly ſubſcribing my ſelf</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>The unworthieſt of your fellow ſervants.</hi> Joh. Brinſley.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Great Yarmouth.</hi> 
                        <date>Jan. 31. 1652.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170076:15"/>
                  <head>TO THE Chriſtian Reader.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>(Chriſtian.)</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I firſt took up this Text, it was far from my thoughts that my <hi>MEDITA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIONS</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhould have been made any further publick, then as the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit rendred them. But ſince that, ſadly laying to heart the long, and yet continued diſuſe of that <hi>Sacred Ordinance,</hi> the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:170076:15"/>of the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> in many places; with the ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and neglecting of it in ſome others, where it is held forth in a regular way, according to the <hi>Primitive Patterne,</hi> I have been induced to caſt abroad this <hi>ſpark,</hi> which <hi>Providence</hi> had put into my hand. Which I have done, not with a deſire of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling any <hi>fire of contention</hi> in the Church (which being already broken forth into ſuch open flames, calls for <hi>water,</hi> not for <hi>oyl,</hi>) but of a <hi>holy zeal,</hi> and <hi>fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor</hi> in the hearts and ſpirits both of <hi>Miniſters</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> that both may be excited in the fear of God, and in obedience to the command of their bleſſed <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Saviour,</hi> ſpeedily to ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome effectual courſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by this <hi>Sealing Ordinance,</hi> being of ſo great concernment to the
<pb facs="tcp:170076:16"/>Church, may be reſtored to <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> with <hi>Purity.</hi> May the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs herein in any degree anſwer my Intentions, I ſhall bleſs God for it, and reſt,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Thine in all Chriſtian ſervices,</hi> John Brinſley.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>YARMOUTH. <date>Jan. 31. 1653.</date>
                        </hi>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170076:16"/>
                  <head>The Saints Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Jeſus Chriſt.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Mat. 26.29.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>But I ſay unto you, I will not henceforth drink of this fruit of the vine, untill that day when I drink it new with you in the kingdom of my father.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving had occaſion in the morning in the Celebration of the bleſſed <hi>Sacrament</hi> of the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> to open unto ſome of you the three verſes fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170076:17"/>wherein we have ſet forth unto us the primitive inſtitution of that Ordinance, I now take hold of theſe words following, which Saint <hi>Luke</hi> annexeth to the <hi>Paſſeover,</hi> Luk. 22.18. but Saint <hi>Matthew</hi> and <hi>Marke</hi> to the <hi>Lords Supper;</hi> not impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably (as <hi>Paraeus</hi> conjectures) they might be twice repeated,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Nihil im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedit quin his idem repetiverit de utro<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> poculo.</hi> Paraeus, ad loc. <hi>Vide</hi> Fulk <hi>&amp;</hi> Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright, <hi>Annot. ad loc.</hi> Parts, Predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Promiſe.</note> as an <hi>Appendix</hi> to both. I ſhall here looke upon them as I meet with them, in reference to the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as relating to the <hi>Euchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Cup,</hi> which the Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrative particle in the Text, <hi>(This) this fruit of the Vine,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> plainly point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth at, as being the next <hi>Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> to it. So looking upon the words, I ſhal take notice in them of two things; a <hi>Prediction,</hi> and a <hi>Promiſe,</hi> or a <hi>Valedicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and a <hi>Conſolation.</hi> The <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction,</hi> or <hi>Valediction</hi> in the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170076:17"/>former part, where our <hi>Saviour</hi> taketh his farewell of his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, of ever having any more ſuch <hi>communion</hi> with them upon earth, and fore-warneth them of his death, being then at hand; <hi>[I ſay unto you, I will not hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth drinke of this fruit of the vine]</hi> The <hi>Promiſe,</hi> or <hi>Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> in the latter, where hee comforteth them with the hope and aſſurance of a better <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion [untill that day when I ſhall drinke it new, &amp;c.]</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Part 1. The Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, or Valedicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> Theſe are the two maine parts of the text, which I ſhall handle ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally and briefly, rather gloſſing upon every thing, then dwelling upon any thing. I begin with the former, the <hi>Prediction,</hi> or <hi>Vale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I will not hence-forth drinke of the fruit of the Vine]</hi> Where the firſt inquiry muſt be,
<note place="margin">The fruit of the vine, what?</note> what we ſhal here underſtand by <hi>this
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170076:18"/>fruit of the Vine;</hi> this ſome have made a queſtion, and (as <hi>Maldonate</hi> ſaith) a <hi>great que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Quid Chriſtus vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem hit appellat, magna eſt queſtio.</hi> Maldonat. ad loc.</note> but without any juſt ground or cauſe that I know; the phraſe is obvious and plaine; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Genimen vitis</hi> (as the vulgar Latine hath it) the <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture,</hi> or product, the <hi>fruit of the Vine</hi> that is, <hi>Wine;</hi> which as elſewhere it is called, <hi>the bloud of the Grape,</hi> Gen. 49.11. ſo here, the <hi>fruit of the vine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Queſt.
<note place="margin">This Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riphraſis why here uſed.</note> But why doth our Saviour here make uſe of this <hi>Periphraſis,</hi> this circumlocuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? why doth he not ſpeake plainly, and ſimply, <hi>I will no more hence-forth drinke of this wine,</hi> or <hi>any wine?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Here (to let other an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers paſſe) that of <hi>Grotius</hi> (and ſome others) ſeemeth moſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall,
<note place="margin">Groti. ad loc. Came<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, Myro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thec. ad loc.</note> who informes us from the <hi>Rabbins,</hi> that this was the uſuall
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170076:18"/>Language in the celebration of the <hi>Paſſeover,</hi> where mentioning the <hi>Cup,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Benedictio ſis tu Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Rex mundi, qui das nobis fructum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis. Maldo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat. ad loc.</note> they were wont to call it by no other name but <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>the fruit of the vine.</hi> So ran their ſet forme of <hi>Benedicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> which the Maſter of the feaſt was wont to uſe in their conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of that <hi>cup. Bleſſed art thou O Lord God, King of the world, who haſt made the fruit of the vines.</hi> And hereupon our <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,</hi> as hee borrowed moſt of thoſe <hi>Sacramental actions</hi> which are uſed in his <hi>Supper</hi> from the <hi>Paſſeover;</hi> ſo alſo he retaineth this phraſe and manner of ſpeech, calling the <hi>Sacramentall Cup,</hi> the <hi>fruit of the vine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> 1.
<note place="margin">The Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Cup, Wine, not Water. <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> in Matth. Hom. 8. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, ibid.</note> Such it was in the firſt inſtitution, <hi>the fruit of the vine, wine,</hi> not <hi>water,</hi> (as <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> obſerves) from this text, againſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170076:19"/>ſome <hi>pernicious Heretickes</hi> in his time (as he calleth them) who cleane contrary to our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours practiſe,
<note place="margin">Joh. 2.9.</note> who <hi>turned water into wine,</hi> they turned the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall wine into water; nor yet <hi>wine mixed with water,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Nor wine mixed with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> (as they of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> will have it, putting a <hi>myſtery</hi> in it) but <hi>pure wine,</hi> the <hi>pure bloud of the grape,</hi> (as it is called, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.14) ſuch it was in the <hi>firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution:</hi> and let not any dare either to <hi>change,</hi> or yet <hi>adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> it with any unwarrantable mixtures.
<note place="margin">Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall elements not to be changed or adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruted.</note> We know what is ſaid of the <hi>Word,</hi> Revel. 22.18. <hi>If any man ſhall adde unto theſe things, God ſhall adde unto him the plagues written in this booke.</hi> And truly of no leſſe dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous conſequence is it, to adde to the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> whether to the <hi>number</hi> of them, or to the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of them, or to the <hi>ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170076:19"/>Ceremonies</hi> about them. Herein let Chriſtians have an eye to the <hi>first patterne,</hi> and cleave as cloſe to that as may be, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either <hi>Addition</hi> or <hi>Subtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction;</hi> both which <hi>Papiſts</hi> are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minently guilty of in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Lords Supper;</hi> of the one in taking away the <hi>Cup</hi> from the people, and ſo giving them but a <hi>halfe Sacrament;</hi> of the other, in mingling <hi>water</hi> with their <hi>wine;</hi> which whatever <hi>ſhew of wiſdome</hi> it may carry with it (as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, thoſe <hi>le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall obſervances</hi> kept alive by ſome in his time did <hi>Col.</hi> 2.23.) yet it is no other but a peice of that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Will-worſhip,</hi> which God will never owne or approve. There is a firſt <hi>Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall wine the ſame before and after Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Obſ. 2. <hi>The fruit of the Vine]</hi> Such was this <hi>Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Cup</hi> before <hi>Conſecration,</hi> and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170076:20"/>ſuch it was after; ſo our Saviour here expreſly calleth it. That <hi>Cup</hi> which in the verſes fore-going he had <hi>bleſſed,</hi> in this verſe he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the <hi>fruit of the vine.</hi> Where then is that <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> which they of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> dreame of? who tell us, that the very <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements</hi> is changed by the <hi>words of Conſecration,</hi> ſo as they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine no longer <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine;</hi> but the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Bloud</hi> of Chriſt, under thoſe <hi>formes</hi> and <hi>appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances:</hi> now ſurely this was a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery which our Saviour took no notice of, which if he had, he would not ſtill have called the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall <hi>Cup,</hi> as here he doth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Conſecration</hi> (as if it were purpoſely to prevent all miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivings about his former figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive expreſſions) the <hi>fruit of the vine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> 3. Againe, this <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170076:20"/>Cup</hi> our Saviour himſelfe here drinketh of,
<note place="margin">Chriſts communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Chryſoſt:</hi> Hom. in <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.28 An argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Manifeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum contra Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubstantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores, &amp; Conſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, Parae ad loc.</hi>
                     </note> ſo much is here plainly intimated and implied <hi>[I will not drinke hence-forth]</hi> ſo then, he had drunke of it at that time, communicating with his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles in eating of the ſame <hi>Bread,</hi> and drinking of the ſame <hi>Cup</hi> with them (which <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> writing upon the former verſe obſerves) and if ſo, here is then another ſtone (as <hi>Paraeus</hi> obſerves) to throw at the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of <hi>Romes Goliah,</hi> their doctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation;</hi> as alſo the <hi>Lutherans</hi> doctrine of <hi>Conſubſtantiation;</hi> both which are ſtrucke dead with this one blow. If Chriſt himſelfe did eate of the Sacramentall <hi>Bread,</hi> and drinke of that Sacramentall <hi>Cup</hi> with his Apoſtles, then certainly it was not (for ſubſtance) his owne <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Bloud.</hi> What ſhall we imagine him to feed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170076:21"/>himſelfe? to eate his owne <hi>fleſh,</hi> to drinke his owne <hi>bloud?</hi> Of all Arguments taken up and made uſe of againſt theſe two dangerous errours, I know none more ſtrongly concluding, and clearly convincing then this; which let it therefore be laid up careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and remembred for the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing of our hearts in the truth of God againſt them.</p>
                  <p>Q.
<note place="margin">Why Chriſt commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated with his Apoſtles in the Supper.</note> 
                     <hi>But it may be demanded, wherefore did our bleſſed</hi> Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our <hi>thus</hi> communicate <hi>with his Apoſtles? Why did he eate of that Sacramentall</hi> Bread? <hi>Why did he drinke of that Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall</hi> Cup? <hi>Had he any need of either?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Not ſo, being himſelfe the <hi>Subſtance,</hi> he had no need of thoſe <hi>ſhadowes;</hi> being himſelfe the <hi>thing ſignified,</hi> he had no need of thoſe <hi>ſignes.</hi> Neither could he expect any benefit to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170076:21"/>himſelfe from this Ordinance, yet he participateth in it; even as before he had ſubmitted himſelfe to the Sacrament of <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> to be baptiſed by <hi>John,</hi> not that he had any need of it (being the <hi>immaculate Lamb of God,</hi> free from all defilement of ſinne, hee needed no waſhing) or expected any benefit by it, but that hee might <hi>fulfill all righteouſneſſe.</hi> So he tels the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> Mat. 3.15. yeelding this as a reaſon of his ſubmiſſion to that Ordinance; <hi>[Thus it becometh us to fulfill all righteouſneſſe.]</hi> To this end he came into the world,
<note place="margin">Chriſt ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe both of the Law and Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel.</note> and this he did, <hi>he fulfilled all righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,</hi> the righteouſneſſe of the <hi>Law;</hi> and thereupon it was that he ſubmitted himſelfe to theſe <hi>legall Ordinances,</hi> the two Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments of the Old Teſtament, <hi>Circumciſion</hi> and the <hi>Paſſeover.</hi> And in like manner he was to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170076:22"/>fulfill all the righteouſneſſe of the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> and thereupon he ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to theſe <hi>Goſpel-Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> the Sacraments of the New Teſtament, <hi>Baptiſme</hi> and the <hi>Supper;</hi> which he did, not for his owne benefit, but ours. Thus was he <hi>Baptized,</hi> that he might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme <hi>Johns</hi> Baptiſme, and <hi>ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie</hi> ours. And thus did he par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take with his Apoſtles in this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the <hi>Supper,</hi> that he might commend it to them and us, teaching us (as by his <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> ſo) by this his <hi>example.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the generall,
<note place="margin">Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans not to ſlight Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances.</note> 
                     <hi>not to ſlight Ordinances;</hi> not to neglect, much leſſe contemn them. What? was the Lord <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe thus <hi>made under Ordinances,</hi> as under <hi>Legall,</hi> ſo under <hi>Goſpel-Ordinances,</hi> and ſhall any that call themſelves <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſet themſelves <hi>above</hi> them? Shall he that was the <hi>Inſtitutor</hi> and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170076:22"/>appointer of Goſpel-Ordinances, as being the <hi>Lord</hi> of them, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit himſelfe to them? and ſhall any who call themſelves his <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,</hi> advance themſelves above them? trampling upon them by a meane and low eſtimation, as if they were <hi>empty and worthleſſe diſpenſations,</hi> as to them? (as ſome of late times have not ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to call them.) To all ſuch let me ſpeake in the words of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> Mat. 10.25. <hi>It is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for the Diſciple that hee be as his maſter, and the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant as his Lord]</hi> Not <hi>above</hi> him; far bee this <hi>Luciferian pride,</hi> this worſt of prides, (ſuch is <hi>ſpirituall pride</hi>) from every of us. Farre be it from us, upon this, or any other ground,
<note place="margin">Among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, not the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</note> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn any Ordinance of God.</p>
                  <p>In particular, not <hi>this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance;</hi> this <hi>ſealing Ordinance,</hi> the Sacrament of the <hi>Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per;</hi>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:170076:23"/>ſlight it not, neglect it not, but with care and conſcience, in obedience to that command <hi>[Doe this]</hi> attend upon it, and make uſe of it, where we may injoy it according to Chriſts Inſtitution. What? doe we ſee our Lord and Maſter <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſitting at Table with his Apoſtles, eating of the Sacramentall <hi>Bread,</hi> and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Sacramentall <hi>Cup,</hi> as it were, <hi>beginning</hi> to them and us; and ſhall not we pledge him, imitate him? It is that which our Saviour telleth his Diſciples, when he had waſhed their feet, <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.15. <hi>I have given you an example</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that yee ſhould doe as I have done]</hi> And the like I may ſay of this his <hi>communicating</hi> with them; here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he gave them and us an <hi>exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> that we ſhould doe as hee did.</p>
                  <p>And great reaſon we ſhould
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170076:23"/>doe ſo; our bleſſed Saviour had no need of this Sacrament, yet partakes of it, to ſhew his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection and obedience to <hi>Goſpel-Inſtitutions.</hi> How much more then ſhould we doe the like, who (if we know our ſelves) cannot but know, that we have conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall need of theſe Ordinances, and this among the reſt, for the confirming and increaſing of our faith, and other Graces in us; which if not fed with theſe Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall viands, are as ſubject to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline and decay, as our bodies through want of our ordinary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt.</p>
                  <p>Be excited then in the feare of God,
<note place="margin">Chriſtians excited to a conſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance upon the Lords Supper.</note> you who now ſtand at a diſtance from this <hi>Ordinance,</hi> and are ſtrangers to it, that you would labour to acquaint your ſelves with it; and for you who have ingaged your ſelves to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend upon it, that you would doe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170076:24"/>it more frequently, more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, more conſcionably.</p>
                  <p>To ſet on which motion let me minde you,
<note place="margin">Chriſt himſelfe preſent at every Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</note> that <hi>you ſhall have Chriſts company at every Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> ſo runs the Promiſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.20. <hi>Where two or three are gathered together in my name, there am I in the midſt of them.]</hi> A promiſe which how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it hath a ſpeciall eye at the adminiſtration of <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Diſcipline,</hi> yet it extendeth ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally to al other religious duties. Where two or three are met to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to <hi>pray,</hi> to <hi>heare</hi> the Word, there will Chriſt afford his preſence in the midſt among them; and ſo he will in the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of this <hi>Sacrament; Chriſt will ever make one at his owne Table,</hi> being alwayes preſent there, though not <hi>corporally</hi> (as he was here with his Apoſtles) yet <hi>ſpiritually.</hi> And that</p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:170076:24"/>
                  <p n="1">1. As a <hi>Spectator,</hi>
                     <note n="1" place="margin">As a Spectator obſerving. 2. The Gueſts which doe come.</note> an <hi>Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> cying (1) the Gueſts; ſo did that <hi>King</hi> in the Parable, when his <hi>Gueſts</hi> were ſet, who came to celebrate the Nuptials of his Sonne, himſelfe cometh in to <hi>ſee them,</hi> Matth. 22.11. Thus doth the Lord Chriſt (the <hi>Maſter of this feaſt</hi>) take a view of all thoſe who preſent themſelves as Gueſts at his Table; ſo as if there bee but one without his <hi>Wedding Garment</hi> (the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>imputed righteouſneſſe,</hi> and <hi>inherent holineſſe,</hi> of which two this Garment is as it were) woven, the one being as the <hi>Woof,</hi> the other as the <hi>Warp)</hi> he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not goe unſpied. Among the <hi>twelve</hi> there was one <hi>Judas,</hi> (who I am ſure was at the <hi>Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over,</hi> and for ought I know might as well be at the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> alſo;) Him the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſuſpect not, when their Maſter told them,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170076:25"/>that <hi>one of them ſhould betray him,</hi> they were every one ready rather to ſuſpect themſelves, then him; <hi>Is it I Maſter? Is it I?</hi> yet our Saviour eſpieth him, and points him out to them. Thus, if there be a <hi>Judas,</hi> an <hi>Hypocrite,</hi> a <hi>cloſe Hypocrite,</hi> (for ſuch a one was he) that ſhal dare at any time to draw nigh to this <hi>Table,</hi> how cloſly ſoever he may carry it, ſo as to deceive all thoſe that ſit at Table with him, yet can he not goe undiſcovered; there is one that ſeeth him, even the <hi>Master of this feaſt,</hi> the Lord Chriſt, who is there preſent, eying and obſerving the Gueſts, taking no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice with what <hi>preparation,</hi> what <hi>diſpoſition,</hi> what <hi>affection</hi> they come to his Table, and how they demeane themſelves being come thither.</p>
                  <p>And whilſt he thus obſerveth thoſe that come,
<note n="2" place="margin">Thoſe which ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</note> hee alſo taketh
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170076:25"/>notice of thoſe who abſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. So did that <hi>King</hi> in the Parable (in the place forena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med:) He was very ſenſible of that diſ-reſpect ſhewne to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the ſlighting of his invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And ſo ſenſible is the <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> of the like diſ-reſpect of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to himſelfe in ſlighting this Ordinance of his, wherein he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth men to have communion with himſelfe; he ſeeth who they are that anſwer the invitations of his Miniſters, with ſuch vain and ſlender excuſes, as too many at this day doe. One liketh not the <hi>company,</hi> amongſt whom he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth ſome not ſo approve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able as they ſhould be, and upon that account hee forbeareth this feaſt, becauſe the hands of ſome of the Gueſts are not ſo cleane waſhed as he conceiveth ſome to be. A ſecond will not endure to be queſtioned by the <hi>Porters,</hi>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:170076:26"/>the <hi>Doore keepers,</hi> what he is, and what he cometh about; I mean, to ſubmit to any <hi>examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> or triall by any <hi>Church-Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers</hi> touching his qualifications, and fitneſſe for that Ordinance. A third ſcruples at the <hi>manner of Administration,</hi> and among all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, the <hi>geſture</hi> now uſed, viz. <hi>ſitting,</hi> eſpecially at the <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> which he looketh upon as too familiar and homely (though it be (for ſubſtance) the very ſame with that wherein our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> at firſt adminiſtred it, and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> received it, which was a <hi>Table geſture,</hi> the ſame that was then uſed at the <hi>Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over,</hi> and at other ordinary meals. A fourth liketh not the tongue that bleſſeth, or the hand that reacheth forth the <hi>Elements.</hi> A fifth (it may be) is not in love and charity with ſome, nor yet deſires to be. Thus doe men caſt
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170076:26"/>ſtumbling blocks in their owne way, finding out ſome pleas and excuſes to keep them from this Ordinance; but whether they be ſuch as will juſtifie this their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſall and neglect, let them ſee to it, knowing that they muſt one day give an account hereof to the <hi>Maſter of this feaſt,</hi> who is thus preſent there as an <hi>Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſecondly,
<note n="2" place="margin">Chriſt preſent as a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municant.</note> as a <hi>Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant,</hi> communicating with thoſe that come. Such is this Sacrament, a <hi>Communion</hi> betwixt Chriſt and the Beleever. <hi>The cup of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing which we bleſſe, is it not the communion of the bloud of Chriſt? The bread which wee breake, is it not the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Body of Chriſt?</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16) A Sacrament, wherein Chriſtians have communion, as one with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, ſo all with Chriſt; who
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170076:27"/>being there ſpiritually preſent, doth (as it were) <hi>ſup with them,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 3.20</note> 
                     <hi>and they with him;</hi> he reaching forth unto them (by the hands of his Miniſters) the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>ſignes,</hi> and together with them the <hi>things ſignified</hi> by them, <hi>Himſelfe,</hi> his owne <hi>Body,</hi> his owne <hi>Bloud.</hi> This he did to his Apoſtles at the inſtitution of this Sacrament, reaching forth the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> to them, hee gave <hi>Him-ſelfe</hi> with them; <hi>Take, eate, this is my Body, this is my Bloud, drinke yee all of it.</hi> And the like he doth ſtill, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever this <hi>Sacrament</hi> is duly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred, Chriſt being there pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, as the Maſter of the Feaſt, he offers and tenders his owne <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Bloud</hi> to thoſe, who upon Goſpel conditions will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him.</p>
                  <p>All which ſhould induce Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to a conſcientious atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170076:27"/>upon this Ordinance, to come to it <hi>readily,</hi> and to uſe it <hi>reverently.</hi> But I promiſed not to dwell upon any thing.</p>
                  <p>We ſee what is here meant by <hi>this fruit of the vine,</hi> and how our Saviour himſelfe drank there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, communicating with his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles in this Sacrament of his Supper, touching which he now giveth them to take notice, that this was <hi>his laſt Supper,</hi> the laſt Sacrament, the laſt meale that ever he ſhould eate with them upon earth. <hi>Hence-forth</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I will not drink of this fruit of the vine.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chriſt knowing his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to be at hand, inſtitutes and cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brates the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Supper.</note>]</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Henceforth]</hi> This our bleſſed Saviour here certainly fore-ſaw, that his <hi>Paſſion</hi> and <hi>departure</hi> were then at hand, that the time was now come, when that <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied</hi> (which himſelfe ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of, verſe thirty one of this Chapter) ſhould be accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170076:28"/>upon him and his, viz. That <hi>the ſhepherd ſhould be ſmitten, and the ſheep of the flock ſhould be ſcattered abroad</hi> (which was made good in his <hi>Paſſion,</hi> where his Diſciples leſt him, every one ſhifting for himſelfe; and that he was now to leave the world, and them in it. Now fore-ſeeing this, he taketh this opportunity for the inſtituting of this <hi>Sacrament</hi> for the uſe of his Church, as alſo, for the holding of <hi>communion</hi> with his Apoſtles; which he did firſt in the <hi>Paſſeover,</hi> and then in the <hi>Supper,</hi> which ſucceeded it. This he did, and that ſo much the rather upon this account. So he tels them concerning the <hi>Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over,</hi> Luk. 22.15. <hi>With deſire have I deſired to eat this Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over with you, before I ſuffer. For I ſay unto you, I will ot any more eate thereof, &amp;c.]</hi> and the like we may conceive concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>Supper.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:170076:28"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> The like are Chriſtians to doe upon a like account, not knowing how ſhort their time may be, how long they ſhall have opportunity; they are</p>
                  <p n="1">1 <hi>To doe good while they may;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chriſtians to doe good while they may.</note> expreſſing their affections to their Brethren while God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth opportunity; ſo doth our <hi>Saſiour</hi> here, knowing that he had not long now to be with his Church upon earth, but that hee was now to drink his laſt draught, he <hi>beginneth a health to it,</hi> let not any catch at the expreſſion, as giving any countenance to their intemperance in drinking of thoſe <hi>Healths,</hi> which are alwayes <hi>ſickneſſe</hi> to the <hi>ſoule,</hi> and often to the <hi>body,</hi> or yet ſtumble at it, it being no other then what the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> maketh uſe of, <hi>Pſal.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 116, 13. <hi>I will take the cup of ſalvation; Calicem ſalutum</hi> (as the Originall hath it) <hi>the cup of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170076:29"/>Healths;</hi> ſo he calleth that <hi>cup</hi> which the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were wont to take and drinke at the offering of their <hi>Euchariſticall Sacrifices,</hi> and giving thankes to God for their deliverances. And the like <hi>cup</hi> our Saviour here taketh, firſt in the <hi>Paſſeover,</hi> then in the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt,</hi> drinking of it, and (as it were) <hi>beginning to his Church,</hi> thereby laying the foundation of an <hi>Ordinance,</hi> which ſhould be of perpetuall uſe unto it in all ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ages. Thus are Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, not knowing how ſhort their time is, they are to <hi>doe good while they may.</hi> So the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle preſſeth it upon his <hi>Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians,</hi> cap. 6.10. <hi>As we have therefore opportunity, let us doe good unto all men, eſpecially to them who are of the houſhold of faith.]</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> whilſt God continueth to us our lives, and putteth advantages into our
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170076:29"/>hands, make uſe of them for the good of others; <hi>working whilſt our day laſteth.</hi> So did our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour, as he tels his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, <hi>Joh.</hi> 9.4. <hi>I muſt work the works of him that ſent me while it is day, the night cometh when no man can work.]</hi> The like do we, knowing that the <hi>night</hi> is coming; it may be the <hi>night of affliction</hi> and trouble, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a time of ſuffering is not ſo fit for working; ſuch a <hi>night</hi> was that which came upon our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in his <hi>Paſſion,</hi> which (ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>chiefe Prieſts and El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi>) he calleth <hi>their houre, and the power of darkneſſe,</hi> Luke 22.53. a time wherein he had not that opportunity of working ſuch workes as formerly he did; or elſe the <hi>night of death,</hi> wherein there is no more work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>There is no worke, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire in the grave whither thou
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170076:30"/>goeſt</hi> (ſaith the Preacher) <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.10. no more doing of good to others. Thoſe <hi>Gifts</hi> or <hi>Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> which God giveth unto men for the uſe and benefit of others, they are only for this life. <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be Propheſies, they ſhall faile, or whether there be Tongues, they ſhall ceaſe</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.8. ſuch gifts ſhall be of no uſe in heaven. And therefore thoſe who are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with any of them, let them improve them now, laying them out in Gods way for the good of their brethren. Thus let Chriſtians be <hi>doing of good.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which they are to doe at all times,
<note place="margin">Specially when they apprehend their change to draw nigh.</note> eſpecially when the <hi>time of their departure ſeemeth to draw nigh.</hi> Thus is it with <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall motions,</hi> the nearer their end the ſwifter they are. Let it be ſo with Chriſtians, to whom God is pleaſed to give any incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170076:30"/>or warning of their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching diſſolution, let them now take all advantages that his providence putteth into their hands, and be (as they may) active and vigorous in the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of them for good, that ſo when they ſhall come to take their leave of, and give their laſt farewell to the world, they may then <hi>ſet,</hi> as the <hi>Sunne</hi> in a cleare evening, and as the <hi>Sonne of righteouſneſſe</hi> here did, full of luſtre and ſplendor, leaving the comfortable warmth and influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of their beames behinde them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <note place="margin">Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove all advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges for their Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual good. Attending upon Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances.</note> And upon the like account Chriſtians are to <hi>receive good,</hi> readily imbracing, and carefully improving all opportunities which God putteth into their hands, for the furthering of their Spirituall welfare, in ſpeciall attending up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his ordinances, <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:170076:31"/>
                  <p n="1">1. <note n="1" place="margin">The Word.</note> Attending upon the <hi>Word,</hi> not knowing but that every Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon may be their laſt, that the Word may be taken from them, or they from the Word, it ought to be their care to attend upon this Ordinance, and to make uſe of it while they have it. This is that our Saviour preſſeth upon the <hi>Jewes,</hi> Joh. 12.35. <hi>Yet a little while</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>is the light with you, walke whilſt you have the light.</hi>] So long as <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> were with them, the light of the Goſpel ſhined a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them; this light he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them to make uſe of, <hi>walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> that is, <hi>beleeving</hi> in it (as the verſe following explaines it) and ſtearing their courſe by it; otherwiſe he tels them what they might expect <hi>[Leſt darkneſſe come upon you]</hi> ſo it did not long after his departure from them, as it was pre-ſignified in that prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170076:31"/>and preter-naturall <hi>Eclipſe</hi> happening at his Paſſion, where the <hi>Sun was darkned at noon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Amos 8.9</note> ſo as <hi>there was darkneſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all the Land</hi> (the Land of Judea) <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.45. A ſad preſage of an inſuing darkneſſe, which not long after came upon that people, a dreadfull darkneſſe, a darkneſſe of <hi>ignorance,</hi> and a darkneſſe of <hi>miſery:</hi> Of <hi>ignorance,</hi> the light being taken from them they were ſtruck with ſpirituall blindneſſe. <hi>I would not brethren have you ignorant of this myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that blindneſſe is in part happened unto Iſrael</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.25. Of <hi>miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> this light being gone, O what a ſad and diſmall day came upon that Nation, <hi>a day of darkneſſe, and of gloomineſs, a day of clouds, and of thicke darkneſſe,</hi> wherein their <hi>Sunne was turned into darkneſſe</hi> (as
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170076:32"/>the Prophet <hi>Joel</hi> deſcribeth the day of their calamity, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.31. ſuch was the <hi>darkneſſe</hi> which came upon that Nation for their not making uſe of the <hi>light</hi> while they injoyed it. The like may they juſtly expect who make no better uſe of the light of the <hi>Word,</hi> whilſt it is continued unto them. Children who play out the Candle that is allowed them, goe to bed in the dark; and what better can they looke for, who trifle away the time and meanes of grace, then that they ſhould goe to bed in the darke, dye without comfort.</p>
                  <p>Which let it take place with you that heare it this day, God is pleaſed as yet to continue unto you the <hi>Goſpel of peace,</hi> and the peace of the Goſpel. As yet the promiſe holdeth good to you, which the Lord maketh unto his people, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.20. Though
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170076:32"/>there bee given unto you <hi>the bread of adverſity, and the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of affliction</hi> (though God be pleaſed to exerciſe you in ſundry kindes, having with-drawne from you many of theſe Temporall mercies which formerly you have injoyed) yet <hi>your Teachers are not removed into corners, but your eyes as yet ſee your Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</hi> But how long this mercy ſhall be continued unto you, who knowes? how ſoone the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds may bee ſmitten, and the ſheep of this fold ſcattered, who can tell? who knoweth but that every Sermon that we preach un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you may be the laſt? And that we ſhall ſpeake no more to you in the name of the Lord. O that this conſideration might worke you to a more conſcientious at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance upon this ordinance.
<note place="margin">The Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Supper.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 And as upon the <hi>Word,</hi> ſo upon the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170076:33"/>of the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> which through the mercy and goodneſs of God is yet held forth unto you in this Congregation, and that in a comfortable way (I meane for the manner of Adminiſtration) as (for ought I know) you ſhall meet with it elſewhere upon earth. This is your <hi>Priviledge,</hi> which many others in this Nation want, and bewaile the want of it. What our Saviour once ſaid to the <hi>Jewes</hi> in his time, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.17. <hi>Many Prophets and righteous men have deſired to ſee the things which you ſee, and have not ſeen them.]</hi> Let mee apply unto you, and to your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent condition; many, both faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Miniſters, and private Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians have deſired, and doe yet deſire to enjoy this Ordinance in ſuch purity, as it is diſpenced in among you, but cannot yet ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine their deſires. But how
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170076:33"/>long this mercy ſhall be continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto you, you know not; hereof you have ſad preſidents in divers parts of this Nation, where the uſe of this Ordinance being for a time unhappily diſcontinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (ſuch is the calamity (that I ſay not the iniquity) of the times) they know not how in any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable way to their owne ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and others, to retrive and recover it againe. My hopes are, that this ſhall not be, and my prayers and indeavours ſhal bee whilſt God continueth me among you, that this may not be your lot; but though this Ordinance be continued unto you, yet you know not how long you ſhall bee continued unto it. Though this <hi>Tree of life</hi> (like that in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> chap. 22.2.) ſhall, (as it hath done) ſtill <hi>yeeld her fruit every moneth,</hi> yet you, (who are to reckon your lives
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170076:34"/>not by <hi>Moneths,</hi> but by <hi>dayes, Few and evill have the dayes of the yeares of my life been</hi> (ſo runs <hi>Jacobs</hi> computation) <hi>Gen.</hi> 17 9. <hi>Man that is borne of a woman is of few dayes</hi> (ſaith <hi>Job,</hi> Job 14.1.) when one Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament is paſt, how doe you know whether you ſhall live to ſee another? And therefore (in the feare of God) upon this ground be perſwaded, you who are capable of it, and in meaſure fit for Sacramentall communion, to a more conſcientious attending upon this Ordinance.</p>
                  <p>Which exhortation let me di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect to two ſorts of perſons:</p>
                  <p n="1">1 You who as yet ſtand aloof off from it,
<note place="margin">The Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Supper not to be neglected.</note> waiting (it may be) to ſee which way the wind will turne, what changes and altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions time may bring forth, that ſo you may more wiſely (as you thinke) comply with it; what
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170076:34"/>know you but that your <hi>change</hi> may be at hand, and may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent (as to you) any other chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. And if ſo, thinke afore-hand how ſadly this may lye upon your ſpirits in the day of ſickneſſe, at the houre of death, that you have upon ſuch ſlight &amp; unwarrantable grounds neglected this Ordinance of God, which (through his bleſſing upon it) might have been of ſpeciall uſe, for the comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and ſtrengthening of your hearts at that time, when you ſhall have moſt need of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 For you,
<note place="margin">But often received.</note> who have given in your names, and new-ingaged your ſelves to a conſcionable at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance upon this, as upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther publick Ordinances of God in this Congregation; doe not you think, that a <hi>quarterly Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> (as was heretofore ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed) wil now ſerve your
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170076:35"/>turne. If this Sacrament be oftner held forth (as in this place it hath been, and I hope ſhall bee) I know not why (without ſome juſt impediment) you ſhould abſent your ſelves from it; you will not doe it by your meales, which ſerve for your bodily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment; ſo oft as your Tables are ſpread you afford your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and why ſhould it not bee thus at <hi>Gods Table?</hi> ſurely thus it would be, were you but as ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of Spirituall decayes as of Corporall, and had but as good an <hi>appetite</hi> to the food of your ſoules, as of your bodies. To quicken which <hi>appetite</hi> lay this conſideration to heart, that you know not how nigh the time of your <hi>Paſſion</hi> or <hi>change</hi> may be; Who knoweth what <hi>Cup,</hi> what bitter cup is coming towards him? or how nigh he may be to his laſt conflict with that laſt enemy,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170076:35"/>Death? wherein all comfort will be little enough; upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count neglect not this <hi>viaticum,</hi> this <hi>ſoveraigne</hi> cordiall, to drink of the fruit of the vine, the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentall Cup,</hi> ſo often as it is by the Miniſters of God, in his name and way, reached forth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you.</p>
                  <p>And thus drinking of it,
<note place="margin">Chriſtians to receive every Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament as their laſt.</note> ever <hi>drinking it as your laſt cup.</hi> So doth our bleſſed <hi>Saviour</hi> here, knowing that it ſhould be ſo. And doe we the like, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but it may be ſo. None of us when we come to the <hi>Table of the Lord,</hi> but may take up our Saviours words, and ſay, that for ought we know, we ſhall <hi>hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth no more drinke of the fruit of the vine,</hi> but that this may be our laſt Sacrament. And ſo look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon it, let it be our care and endeavour, as (when we come) to come with due preparation, ſo
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170076:36"/>in the act of receiving to raiſe up our hearts, that what wee doe, we may doe it with all our might, with all poſſible intention of ſoule and ſpirit; certainly this we would do, were we but aſſured (as our <hi>Saviour</hi> here was) that the preſent Sacrament ſhould be our laſt; O how would we then bend our ſpirits to the duty? Do we the like at every Sacrament, not knowing but it may be ſo; ſo eating the Sacramentall. <hi>Bread,</hi> and ſo drinking the Sacramentall <hi>Cup,</hi> as if it were our laft farewell to all Creature-comforts, and Ordinances. So doth our bleſſed Saviour here, celebrating of this Feaſt with his Apoſtles, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving drunke of that Sacramentall <hi>Cup; Henceforth</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I ſhall drink no more of this fruit of the vine.]</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Part 2. The Pto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, or Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> There is his <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction,</hi> or <hi>Valediction.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Conſolation</hi> or <hi>Promiſe</hi>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:170076:36"/>followeth <hi>[untill that day, when I drinke it new with you in the kingdome of my Father.]</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Untill,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A word ſpoken in ſeaſon.</note> a word ſpoken in ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which (as the <hi>Wiſe-man</hi> ſaith) is <hi>verbum bonum,</hi> a <hi>good word,</hi> Prov. 15.23. <hi>Like apples of gold, with pictures of ſilver, Prov.</hi> 25.11. Amiable and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable; ſuch was this <hi>[Untill]</hi> unto the Apoſtles here, who could not but be much troubled at the former words, to heare that their Maſter and they muſt now part, that this was the laſt meale that ever they were like to have toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; this could not but be a ſadding to their ſpirits. So was it to the <hi>Elders</hi> of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> when <hi>Paul</hi> told them, that they ſhould <hi>ſee his face no more,</hi> Act. 20.25. This made a deep impreſſion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their ſpirits (as the laſt verſe of that Chapter informes us.) <hi>And they all wept ſore</hi> (ſaith
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170076:37"/>the thirty ſeventh) <hi>and fell on</hi> Pauls <hi>neck and kiſſed him, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing moſt of all for the words which he ſpake, that they ſhould ſee his face no more.]</hi> To think what loſſe themſelves and the Church ſhould have in <hi>Pauls</hi> death, this ſtrucke them to the heart; and queſtionleſſe it could not but doe the like to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles here, to heare the like from their <hi>maſter;</hi> that he and they muſt now part, that this was the laſt <hi>Cup</hi> that ever hee ſhould drinke with them; this could not but be a ſad word to them. To allay this griefe, he therefore pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fently ſubjoynes this <hi>conſolatory promiſe,</hi> ſtaying their hearts, and comforting them with the hope and aſſurance of another, and a better <hi>communion</hi> one day; <hi>[Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till that day, when I ſhall drinke it new with you in my Fathers kingdom.]</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:170076:37"/>
                  <p>Q. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>Vntill that day]</hi> But what <hi>day</hi> was that? a queſtion,
<note place="margin">What day is here ſpoken of?</note> and a great queſtion among Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitors; a four-fold opinion I finde about it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1.
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <note place="margin">A four-fold opinion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it. <hi>A.</hi> 1. The time of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours abode upon earth, after his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</note> Some (in the firſt place) underſtand it of the <hi>time of our Saviours abode upon earth after his reſurrection;</hi> during which time he had <hi>communion</hi> with his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> appearing to them, and converſing with them; which he did at ſundary times for forty dayes together (as Saint <hi>Luke</hi> reports it, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.3.) And thus converſing with them, he alſo <hi>ate</hi> with them; this hee did more then once. So wee finde him, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.41. where com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to his Diſciples, hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of them. <hi>Have yee here any meat? And they giving him a peice of broyled Fiſh, and an Hony-combe, He tooke it,</hi> (ſaith the text) <hi>and did eate
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170076:38"/>before them.]</hi> The like we finde again, <hi>John</hi> 21. where our <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> putting the like queſtion to <hi>Peter,</hi> and ſome of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> with him, <hi>Children, have ye any meat?</hi> Verſ. 5. Afterwards he dined with them upon their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous draught of fiſhes, <hi>Ver.</hi> 12, 13. And thus <hi>eating</hi> with them, (though it be not expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, yet) it is more then probable, that he alſo <hi>drank</hi> with them. So much is collected from that ſpeech of <hi>Peter</hi> to <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his company,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Petrus non dixit Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſe ac bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſſe cum diſcipulis, ſed diſcipu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſe ac bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſſe cum Chriſto.</hi> Camer. Myrothec. in Act. 10.41.</note> 
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 20.41. where ſpeaking of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> he tells them, <hi>God ſhewed him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, who did eat and drink with him, after he roſe from the dead.]</hi> This did <hi>Peter,</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles: And they eating and drinking with him, (by the leave of that learned <hi>Came<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi>) it cannot well be conceived, but that he did the like with
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170076:38"/>them; both <hi>eat</hi> and <hi>drink</hi> with them. And drinking with them, not improbably he might drink <hi>wine</hi> alſo, which was no unuſual drink in that Countrey. And to this, ſome conceive this ſpeech of his here to relate.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chryſoſt. Theophy l. Euthym. Bez. Gr. Aun.</hi> This Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition diſallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for 3 Reaſons. <hi>Maldonat. ad loc.</hi>
                     </note> So divers of the <hi>Antients</hi> (to whom <hi>Beza</hi> ſeemeth not averſe) look upon this place.</p>
                  <p>But with them I cannot go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long. Three Reaſons I finde given againſt this Expoſition: A firſt, taken from theſe words <hi>[Till that day]</hi> which ſeemeth (ſaith <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donate</hi>) to point at ſome remoter time, then this. Secondly, Our <hi>Saviour</hi> was not as yet entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his <hi>Fathers Kingdom;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Calvin ad loc.</note> being in that interval, in a middle ſtate, betwixt <hi>mortality and glory,</hi> as himſelf telleth <hi>Mary,</hi> John 20.17. <hi>Touch me not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>for I am not yet aſcended unto my Father.</hi>] But thirdly, ſhould we
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170076:39"/>ſuppoſe him then in his <hi>Fathers Kingdom</hi> (as he was upon the confines of it,
<note place="margin">Calvin ib.</note> being then in a ſtate of <hi>immortality</hi>) yet the like can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid of his Apoſtles, their condition being not yet changed. Upon theſe grounds, I ſhall lay aſide this firſt <hi>Expoſition.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>2</label>
                     <note place="margin">The day of Pente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coft.</note> Others (in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place) by <hi>[That day]</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand <hi>The day of Pentecoſt.</hi> Of this <hi>day</hi> our <hi>Saviour</hi> had ſpoken to his Apoſtles before, telling them, that then they ſhould <hi>ſee the Kingdom of God come with power.</hi> So Saint <hi>Mark</hi> ſets it down, <hi>Chap.</hi> 9.1. <hi>Verily I ſay unto you, that there be ſome of them which ſtand here, who ſhall not taſte of death, till they have ſeen the Kingdom of God come with power.</hi>] So it did at that <hi>day,</hi> when after our <hi>Saviours Aſcenſion,</hi> the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> was poured out upon the Apoſtles in
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170076:39"/>ſuch a wonderful manner, to the admiration of all the beholders; in ſo much, that ſome of them ſpared not to ſay, <hi>That they were full of new wine, Acts</hi> 2.13. Now did the Kingdom of God come with power;
<note place="margin">Carthuſ. ad loc.</note> the Goſpel being by this means wonderfully propagated. And here (ſay ſome) was this promiſe made good: Here did <hi>Chriſt, coming in his Kingdom</hi> (as Saint <hi>Matthew</hi> hath it, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.28.) <hi>drink this fruit of the Vine new with his Apoſtles;</hi> Communicating unto them ſuch extraordinary gifts and graces.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>3</label> Others (in the ſecond place) by <hi>[That day]</hi> underſtand the time, or <hi>Kingdom of Grace,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The time of Grace under the Goſpel. <hi>Beda. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron.</hi>
                     </note> under the Goſpel: This is oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times called the <hi>Kingdom of God.</hi> And in this Kingdom, <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath a <hi>Communion,</hi> a ſweet <hi>Communion</hi> with his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170076:40"/>as it were <hi>eating and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> with them. This he doth <hi>Sacramentally</hi> in his Supper; where he may be ſaid to <hi>drink this wine new</hi> with them at every communion. And this he doth <hi>ſpiritually,</hi> by communicating the Graces and Comforts of his <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> unto them. Such is that <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> which he maketh pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of, to every one that will <hi>hear his voice</hi> (the voice of the Goſpel) <hi>and open the door,</hi> (the door of his heart, to receive, and entertain him by Faith and Love.) <hi>I will come</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and ſup with him, and he with me, Revel.</hi> 3.20. That is, Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate Graces and Comforts to him, holding a comfortable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him. Thus doth <hi>Christ</hi> (as it were) <hi>feaſt</hi> with his people upon Earth, bringing them into his <hi>Banquetting Houſe,</hi> (or <hi>Houſe of Wine</hi>) (as the Spouſe
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170076:40"/>phraſeth it, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.4) the <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Aſſemblies,</hi> where his <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances</hi> are as ſo many <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duits, running with the beſt wine;</hi> through which, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyeth pureſt and choiceſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts to the hearts of his people, chearing and refreſhing them; and in a <hi>ſpiritual way,</hi> (as it were) <hi>inebriating</hi> them, as the vulgar <hi>Latine</hi> renders that of the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> Pſal. 36.8. <hi>Inebria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buntur ab ubertate domus tuae, They ſhall be inebriated with the plentiful fulneſs of thy houſe.</hi> And in a like ſenſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> may be ſaid to have <hi>drunk of the fruit of the Vine,</hi> with his <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> after his <hi>Aſcenſion;</hi> ſtill holding communion with them, being abſent from them <hi>in Body,</hi> yet he was preſent with them <hi>in Spirit;</hi> ſending the <hi>Comforter</hi> to them. This he promiſed to do, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.16. &amp; 15.26. And this
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170076:41"/>he did, thereby ſupplying the want of his bodily preſence, and filling their hearts with joy, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as he had promiſed he would do,
<note place="margin">Both theſe expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allowed.</note> 
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.24.</p>
                  <p>But I ſhall not dare to vouch either of theſe Expoſitions more then the former. The <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> which our Saviour here per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto his Apoſtles, he ſaith it ſhould be in <hi>the Kingdome of his Father;</hi> which terme, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive cannot ſo fitly bee applied either to the <hi>day of Pentecoſt,</hi> or yet to the <hi>Kingdome of Grace;</hi> which though it be ſometimes called the <hi>Kingdome of God,</hi> and of <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 17.21 Ioh. 18.36. <hi>Regnum Patris nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam niſi caelum vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catur. Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. ad loc.</hi> The king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of glory.</note> and oft times the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven, yet never doe we finde it called the <hi>Kingdome of the Father,</hi> (as <hi>Maldonate</hi> well obſerves.)</p>
                  <p>In the fourth place then, (to hold you no longer in ſuſpence) underſtand we this of the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170076:41"/>of glory.</hi> This is the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Kingdome. [Then ſhall the righteous ſhine forth as the Sunne in the Kingdome of their Father</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.43. that is, in the Kingdome of Heaven, the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of glory. And this our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour calleth the <hi>Kingdome of his Father.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of glory the Fathers kingdom. <hi>Solus pater non deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit de caele, Maldon. ad text. Lorinus</hi> in Act. 10.44 The king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of glory the place of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, Joh. 1.14.</note> So is the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Glory,</hi> in a peculiar way, the <hi>Fathers Kingdome.</hi> I finde two reaſons given for it.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 In as much as there hath been the <hi>Fathers Reſidence,</hi> there hath he manifeſted the preſence of his <hi>Glory</hi> in a more conſtant and continued way then either of the other perſons; As for the <hi>Son,</hi> the <hi>ſecond Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> he came down from Heaven, and was Incarnate, leaving the boſome of the Father hee came <hi>and dwelt amongſt us,</hi> diſ-ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing himſelfe of his Majeſty and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170076:42"/>glory, he tooke upon him the <hi>forme of a Servant.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Phil. 2.7.</note> And the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> the third perſon here deſcended upon him,
<note place="margin">Joh. 15.26</note> and after his Aſcenſion was as it were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed by him as his <hi>Agent,</hi> each of them occaſionally appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and manifeſting their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence upon earth in ſeverall tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions; but <hi>the Father</hi> in the meane time ſtill kept the Throne of his glory in Heaven, ſhewing himſelfe the King thereof.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 But (ſecondly,
<note place="margin">The Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidency of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of glory, reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Father.</note> and as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive more genuinely) the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Father,</hi> in as much as the <hi>precedency</hi> and chiefe Government of that Kingdome ſhall for ever reſt in him. As for the <hi>Kingdome of Grace,</hi> that is committed to the <hi>Sonne,</hi> who ſitting at the right hand of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Heaven, <hi>ruleth in the midſt of his enemies</hi> upon earth; but the <hi>Kingdome of Glory</hi> is
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170076:42"/>more peculiarly the <hi>Fathers,</hi> to whom the <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> ſhall at the laſt day reſigne up that his <hi>Oeconomicall Kingdome</hi> (as they call it.) That Kingdome which as <hi>Mediator</hi> he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from his Father, he ſhall then ſurrender it up unto him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, as the Apoſtle tels us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24. <hi>Then cometh the end, when he ſhall have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered the Kingdom unto God, even the Father.]</hi> So as from thence-forth and for ever that Kingdome ſhall be the <hi>Fathers Kingdome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And in this Kingdome it is that our <hi>Saviour</hi> here promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to his Apoſtles this <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> telling them, that hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth he would no more <hi>drink of the fruit of the vine, untill that day that he ſhould drink it new with them in that Kingdom,</hi> the Kingdome of Heaven.</p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:170076:43"/>
                  <p>Object. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>But underſtanding the words thus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Did not Chriſt eat and drink with his Apoſtles, after his Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> 
                     <hi>here an obvious objection meeteth us. What, did not Chriſt eat and drink with his Apostles upon Earth, after his Reſurrection?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. To this it is anſwered by ſome, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> That though he then <hi>ate</hi> with them,
<note place="margin">A three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. <hi>Peſt reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectionem comediſſe legitur, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſſe vero non legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roth. ad loc. <hi>Nec erat moris apud Judaeos bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere vinum in prandiis ac caenis quotidianis, ſed tantum in ſolemnioribus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viviis.</hi> Piſcat. Schol. ad loc.</note> yet there is no mention made of his <hi>drinking</hi> with them. And ſo <hi>non creditur, quià non legitur;</hi> being not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded, we are not bound to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve it. But this I have already ſhown to be a miſtake.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Suppoſing that he did alſo <hi>drink</hi> with them, yet there is no neceſſity, to conclude, that he drank <hi>wine</hi> with them. Nay it is more probable (ſaith <hi>Piſcator</hi>) that he did not, in as much (ſaith he) as it was not the cuſtom of the Jews to drink wine at their
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170076:43"/>common and ordinary meals, but onely at their more ſolemn <hi>Feaſts</hi> and <hi>Banquets.</hi> But this alſo may ſeem to be an <hi>evaſion,</hi> rather then a <hi>ſolution;</hi> and therefore I ſhall not flie to it, neither need I.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Yeeld it, that our Saviour,
<note place="margin">Chriſts eating and drinking with his Apoſtles, after his Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, no natural actions. <hi>Maldon. ad loc.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Chryſoſt. Hom. in Text. Calvin. Maldon. ad loc.</hi>
                     </note> as he <hi>ate,</hi> ſo he <hi>drank</hi> with his Apoſtles, and that, <hi>wine</hi> alſo, (which <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> taketh for granted) yet did he not now do it <hi>humano, &amp; conſueto more,</hi> ſo as formerly he had done, and as he did at this his laſt <hi>Supper.</hi> He did not now, either eat or drink for any bodily nouriſhment or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment, having no more need of meats or drinks, nor yet in a way of <hi>ſocial communion;</hi> one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the confirming of the Faith of his Apoſtles in the certainty of his Reſurrection, he ſhewed them what he could do. So as he did there (as it were) <hi>eat and not eat, drink and not drink.</hi> Even
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170076:44"/>as ſpeaking to his Apoſtles after his Reſurrection, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.44. he tells them, <hi>Theſe are the words which I ſpake unto you, while I was yet with you.]</hi> Why, was he not then with them, when he thus ſpake to them? Yes, but not as formerly, when he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed with them in a terreſtrial and temporal life. So he ate and drank with them now, but not as formerly.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Quià id non niſi ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luti per tranſennam fecit, non ducit in nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merum.</hi> Maldon.</note> This was not in him now any natural action; and therefore he overlooketh it, as being a thing by the <hi>by:</hi> Telling his Apoſtles, that he would not any more thus <hi>drink</hi> with them, until that day when he ſhould do it in the Kingdom of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                     </label>
                     <note place="margin">The fruit of the Vine, how drunk in Heaven.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>But how ſaith he, that he would then do it? What is there any eating or drinking in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label>
                     <note place="margin">Not lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally.</note> Not ſo. This is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170076:44"/>for <hi>Mahumetans,</hi> not ſo <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> Eating and drinking are for Earth, not for Heaven. Even as our Saviour anſwering the carnal reaſonings of the <hi>Saddu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> againſt the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> tells them, <hi>That in the Reſurrection they neither marry, nor are given in marriage, but are as the Angels of God in Heaven,</hi> Matth. 22.30. In the ſtate of glory, Gods Saints ſhall live an <hi>Angelical life;</hi> no more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to any bodily neceſſities, or infirmities. Not ſtanding in need of <hi>marriage,</hi> or yet of <hi>meats</hi> and <hi>drinks. The Kingdom of God is not meat and drink,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, ſpeaking of the <hi>Kingdom of Grace, Rom.</hi> 14.17. much leſs the <hi>Kingdom of glory,</hi> where there is no need, no uſe of either; and therefore away with all ſuch groſs and carnal ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations. For our ſatisfaction
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170076:45"/>taking notice,
<note place="margin">But my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtically and meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorically.</note> that theſe phraſes of <hi>eating and drinking</hi> are in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture uſed in a double ſenſe. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>literally</hi> and <hi>properly,</hi> ſometimes <hi>myſtically</hi> and <hi>meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorically.</hi> And both theſe ways is this word <hi>[Drinking]</hi> uſed in this verſe. In the former part of it <hi>properly,</hi> for <hi>natural</hi> and <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral drinking;</hi> in the latter part <hi>metaphorically,</hi> for <hi>myſtical</hi> and <hi>ſpiritual drinking.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And what we ſay of the <hi>act,</hi> we may ſay alſo of the <hi>object.</hi> The <hi>fruit of the vine,</hi> which our Saviour did drink of, as in the <hi>Paſſeover,</hi> ſo in his <hi>Supper,</hi> was <hi>natural Wine;</hi> that which here he promiſeth to drink of, is <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical</hi> and <hi>Spiritual.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The ſame word uſed in two dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the ſame ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Neither let any here ſtumble at this ſo ſudden a change of the ſenſe. That the ſame words ſhould be with one and the ſame breath, in one and the ſame ſentence, uſed
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170076:45"/>in two different ſenſes. This be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no unuſual thing in Scripture; no other then what we finde often practiſed by our <hi>Saviour</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Non ſolàm ſine vitio, ſed cum magnâ eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am oraii<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis elegan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ.</hi> Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. ad loc.</note> and that not onely without any <hi>abſurdity</hi> (as <hi>Maldonate</hi> notes upon it) but with a <hi>ſpecial elegance</hi> and <hi>accurateneſs</hi> of Speech. Thus ſpeaking to that <hi>Diſciple,</hi> who being invited to follow him, deſired that he might <hi>firſt go and bury his Father,</hi> (be aſſiſtant unto him in his decrepit age, and perform his laſt office to him, when he ſhould dye) <hi>Let the dead</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>bury their dead, Matth.</hi> 8.22. Let them that are <hi>ſpiritually dead,</hi> bury them that are <hi>corporally dead:</hi> Thoſe who are <hi>dead in ſin,</hi> bury thoſe that are <hi>dead for ſin.</hi> So again, ſpeaking to the <hi>Woman of</hi> Samaria, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.13, 14. He tells her, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall drink of this water, ſhall thirſt again:
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170076:46"/>But whoſoever ſhall drink of the water that I ſhall give him, ſhall never thirſt.]</hi> Where in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part, he ſpeaketh of <hi>natural water,</hi> ſuch as ſhe gave him: In the latter part of <hi>myſtical</hi> and <hi>ſpiritual water, viz.</hi> The Grace and Spirit of Regeneration. And ſo are we to underſtand that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, <hi>Mark</hi> 10.15. where our <hi>Saviour</hi> bleſſing the <hi>children</hi> which were brought to him, tells his <hi>Diſciples, That whoſoever ſhall not receive the Kingdom of God, as a little childe, he ſhall not enter therein.</hi> Where by the <hi>Kingdom of God</hi> in the former part, we are to underſtand the <hi>Doctrine of the Kingdom,</hi> the <hi>Gospel;</hi> In the latter part, the <hi>Heavenly Kingdom, Eternal life</hi> and <hi>glory.</hi> And the very like do we here meet within the Text. <hi>Drinking of the fruit of the Vine,</hi> in the former part it is to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170076:46"/>be underſtood <hi>properly,</hi> of <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral wine,</hi> in the latter part <hi>my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtically</hi> of <hi>ſpiritual wine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſo much is not obſcurely inſinuated in that <hi>Addition,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Celeſtial Glory cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led New Wine.</note> which is here put to it, where it is called <hi>New Wine. Until I drink it new.</hi> Thus the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Scripture,</hi> is wont for the moſt part (as it were) <hi>emol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lire Allegorias,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Solent</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamento e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molliri.</hi> Grot. ad loc.</note> to <hi>ſoften Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gories,</hi> which otherwiſe might ſeem hard, by ſome ſuch addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taments. As the Apoſtle ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>blood,</hi> he calleth it <hi>Spiritual drink,</hi> and him a <hi>Spiritual rock,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4. Thus Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to beleevers, he tells them, <hi>That they as [lively ſtones] were built up a [ſpiritual houſe] an holy Prieſthood to offer up [ſpiritual ſacrifice.]</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. In like manner the <hi>Spirit</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Rome,</hi> (or the <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire)
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170076:47"/>where the Bodies of Gods Saints ſhould lie ſlain, he ſtiles it, <hi>That great City, which ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally is called</hi> Sodom <hi>and</hi> Egypt, <hi>Revel.</hi> 11.8. Not literally, but myſtically; and ſuch is this <hi>Wine</hi> which our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſaith here he would drink of in his Fathers Kingdom; not <hi>natural,</hi> but <hi>my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical wine,</hi> which he therefore calleth <hi>new.</hi> Even as the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> whereof <hi>Old Jeruſalem</hi> was a Type, is called <hi>The New Jeruſalem, Revel.</hi> 21.2. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that is, Not the <hi>earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> but the <hi>Heavenly</hi> Jeruſalem, Jeruſalem <hi>which is above,</hi> (as the Apoſtle calleth it) <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.26. Even thus our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Celeſtial glory,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Wine an embleme of Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. <hi>Vide Grot. ad Text.</hi>
                     </note> and happineſs here, he calleth it <hi>New Wine,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that is, Wine of another kinde, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> (as <hi>Grotius</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains it) <hi>Intellectual, Spiritual Wine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:170076:47"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wine.]</hi> Thus the <hi>Rabbinical Jews</hi> were wont to ſet forth <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life,</hi> by <hi>wine kept from the beginning of the world,</hi> from the firſt Creation. And the like ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God</hi> may be conceived ſometimes to make uſe of. In that 55 of <hi>Iſaiah, v.</hi> 1. <hi>Chriſt</hi> is brought in making Proclamation, <hi>Ho, every one that thirſteth, &amp;c. Come and buy wine and milk;</hi> Under thoſe two words comprehending all ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and heavenly bleſſings, <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Glory.</hi> And thus do ſome underſtand that Speech of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to his Church, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.1. Where he tells her, <hi>I have drunk my wine, with my milk.]</hi> This he did (as he ſaith) in his <hi>Garden,</hi> by which they underſtand the <hi>Heavenly Paradiſe,</hi> where he promiſed the penitent theef to meet him. Here doth <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace himſelf, after all his ſorrows
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170076:48"/>and ſufferings upon earth, injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing celeſtiall glory and happineſs: This he here calleth by the name of <hi>Wine,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Reſemb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of it:</note> 
                     <hi>[the fruit of the vine.]</hi> and that not unfitly:</p>
                  <p n="1">1 <hi>Wine</hi> is a generous, ſweet, and <hi>delectable</hi> liquor, moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to the pallate, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label>
                     <note place="margin">Wine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectable.</note> and gratefull to the ſtomack, one of the preciouſeſt juyces that the earth produceth. Hence it is that the <hi>mutuall love</hi> betwixt <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Church</hi> is compared to <hi>Wine,</hi> and preferred before it, <hi>Thy love is better then wine</hi> (ſaith the Church to Chriſt) <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.2. <hi>How much better is thy love then wine?</hi> (ſaith Chriſt to his Church) <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.10. more ſweet, more pleaſant; ſuch is the <hi>glory of Heaven,</hi> yeelding an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable complacency to the ſoule; ſuch as none can appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, but they that are poſſeſſed of it: Even as none can tell how
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170076:48"/>grateful and delectable <hi>Wine</hi> is, but they who have taſted of it. So is it with heavenly bliſs, ſuch is the excellency of it, as none can conceive, but thoſe who are entred into it, and ſwallowed up of it. <hi>Eye hath not ſeen, ear hath not heard, neither hath it entred into the heart of man, what things God hath prepared for them that love him.</hi> 1 Cor. 2.9.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Wine,</hi> as it is delectable, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> ſo it is <hi>cordial;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Wine Cordial.</note> not onely pleaſing the pallate, but chearing the heart. <hi>Should I leave my wine,</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Vine</hi> in <hi>Jothams</hi> parable) <hi>which cheareth God and man,</hi> Judg. 9.13. <hi>Wine maketh glad the heart of man</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi>) <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.15. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Solomon</hi> (called by the name of <hi>Lemuel,</hi> that is, <hi>of God,</hi> a King of <hi>Gods</hi> making) <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.6. adviſeth <hi>to give wine to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170076:49"/>thoſe that are of heavy hearts.</hi> Wine being of a ſpirituous nature, it exhilarateth the ſpirits, <hi>it maketh merry, Eccleſ.</hi> 10.19. And in this property again, it is a fit embleme of heavenly joy: Where ever the <hi>Kingdom of God</hi> is, there is <hi>joy.</hi> It is ſo with his <hi>Kingdom of Grace,</hi> of which the Apoſtle tells us, that it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in <hi>Righteouſneſs, Peace, and Joy, Rom.</hi> 14.17. much more in his <hi>Kingdom of glory</hi> there is <hi>joy. Enter thou into thy maſters joy, Matth.</hi> 25.23. And nothing but joy. Here upon Earth the <hi>Chriſtians Wine</hi> is mixed with <hi>water;</hi> his joys and comforts are allayed with a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of croſſes and ſorrows. But in Heaven there is <hi>pure wine,</hi> pure joy; and that <hi>fulneſs of joy. In his preſence is fulneſs of joy, Pſal.</hi> 16. laſt. It is ſo in Heaven, at Gods right hand, in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170076:49"/>of his glory. Thus <hi>celeſtial happineſs</hi> is ſet forth under the name of <hi>wine.</hi> And that</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>New wine]</hi> So called,
<note place="margin">Celeſtial glory, why called new wine.</note> not onely becauſe it is of another kinde (as I ſaid) but of a <hi>better,</hi> a more <hi>excellent kinde.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Soleut He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braei quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanthus eſt, atque ſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius, novum appellare.</hi> Maldon. ad loc. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>excellenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am. Sic &amp;</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, Apoc. 2.17. &amp; 3.12. <hi>Novum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam apud latinos di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid egregium eſt. Pollio &amp; ipſe amat nova carmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi>—Camer. Myorth. ad Text.</note> Thus the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> (as <hi>Maldonate</hi> noteth upon it) are wont to call a thing that is excellent, <hi>New. O ſing unto the Lord a new ſong,</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi>) <hi>Pſal.</hi> 96.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 98.1. that is, (as he expounds it) an excellent ſong. In this ſenſe (among others) the <hi>Gospel</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand concerning <hi>love,</hi> may be called a <hi>New commandment,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.7, 8. and the <hi>Gospel covenant,</hi> a <hi>new covenant, Heb.</hi> 8.8. And ſuch is this <hi>wine</hi> in the Kingdom of God, <hi>new wine,</hi> true <hi>Nectar</hi> (which the Poets fained to be the drink of the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170076:50"/>gods) of a more excellent kinde then any here upon Earth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thus doth Chriſt ſtill reſerve the beſt wine to the laſt:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chriſt ſtill reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the beſt wine to the laſt.</note> So he did in a <hi>literal ſenſe</hi> at that marriage feaſt in <hi>Cana</hi> of <hi>Gali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lee,</hi> which he graced with his own preſence, as the <hi>Maſter</hi> or <hi>Ruler of the feaſt</hi> tells him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.10. And this he doth in a <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual</hi> ſenſe. As he did here for himſelf, ſo for his Saints he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth their <hi>beſt wine</hi> for the laſt; not ſo with <hi>wicked men.</hi> They drink their beſt wine firſt;
<note place="margin">Not ſo for wicked men.</note> having their <hi>portion in this life,</hi> here they meet with many carnal comforts and contentments, which it may be the deareſt Saints of God want. But their worſt is to come. So our Saviour telleth them, <hi>Luke</hi> 6.25, 26. <hi>Wo unto you that are full, for ye ſhall hunger; wo unto you that laugh now, for ye ſhall mourn and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170076:50"/>weep.</hi> Here they have their <hi>ſweet wine,</hi> but there is ſower and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wine reſerved for them; even that wine which is prepared for <hi>Babylon,</hi> Rev. 14.10. <hi>The wine of the wrath of God, which is poured out without mixture into the cup of his indignation.</hi> Of this <hi>wine</hi> ſhall the <hi>worſhippers of the Beaſt</hi> drink, all <hi>Idolaters,</hi> and with them all other wicked &amp; ungodly men.
<note place="margin">But for his Saints.</note> But it ſhal be otherwiſe with Gods Saints and Servants. Here it may be God may deale with them as the <hi>Jews</hi> dealt with our Savior, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.34. when they gave him <hi>Gall and vineger to drinke;</hi> he may <hi>make them drink the wine of aſtoniſhment</hi> (as the Pſalmiſt complains, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 60.3.) <hi>wringing out unto them waters of a full cup</hi> (as he elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where ſpeaketh <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.10.) laying out unto them a large meaſure of ſore afflictions; But
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170076:51"/>there is better <hi>Wine</hi> reſerved for them hereafter. <hi>New wine,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent wine, joy infinitely tranſcending all joyes earth can af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford: This was Chriſts portion, and this ſhall be their portion; So much they are aſſured of, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.13, 14. <hi>Therefore thus ſaith the Lord God, Behold my ſervants ſhal eate, but ye ſhal be hungry, behold, my ſervants ſhal drink, but ye ſhal be thirſty; behold, my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants ſhall rejoyce, but ye ſhall be aſhamed; Behold my ſervants ſhall ſing for joy of heart, but yee ſhall cry for ſorrow of heart, and ſhall howle for vexation of ſpirit.]</hi> Such a change can God make in the affairs of this world, and I doubt not but he will yet doe it in a great meaſure for his Church in the latter daies, to which that promiſe ſeems to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late: But however ſuch a change there ſhall be hereafter: There
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170076:51"/>is <hi>wine, new wine</hi> reſerved and laid up for the Saints in heaven, which the men of this world ſhall never taſt of. This <hi>wine</hi> our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vior here promiſeth to himſelfe, that he ſhould drink of it, which accordingly not long after he did upon his <hi>aſcention</hi> into heaven, then having finiſhed his ſuffering worke, he <hi>entered into his reſt,</hi> from thenceforth injoying un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable <hi>glory</hi> and <hi>happineſſe.</hi> And herein he tells his Apoſtles that they ſhould alſo have a ſhare with him. So it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; <hi>Untill that day,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Judas</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, though not from Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, yet from Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with Chriſt.</note> 
                     <hi>when I ſhall drinke it new with you.] with you]</hi> What, with all of them? not ſo, if <hi>Judas</hi> were in the company; which ſome conceive that he was not, taking up this for an argument againſt it, becauſe Chriſt here promiſeth to thoſe who dranke of that <hi>cup</hi> with him in the Sacrament of his Supper,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170076:52"/>that he would drink it <hi>new</hi> with them;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vobiſcum ad plures, non ad om. ner referen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſt.</hi> Aquin. ad loc.</note> a matter wherein <hi>Judas</hi> had neither <hi>part</hi> nor <hi>lot.</hi> But ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing him to be there, yet wil not this create any great difficulty, the <hi>promiſe</hi> being <hi>indefinite,</hi> not <hi>univerſall,</hi> extending to the generality of them; to as many of them as had there not onely a <hi>Sacramentall,</hi> but alſo a <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall communion</hi> with him. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>
                     </label> 
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>With all ſuch will Jeſus Chriſt drink this new wine in his Fathers Kingdom;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Such as have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Chriſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth, ſhall have communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with him in Heaven.</note> have a bleſſed communion with them in heaven.</p>
                  <p>Marke it, this is the Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation which I have been long making way to. <hi>Such as have communion with Jeſus Chriſt upon earth ſhall have commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with him in heaven.</hi> Chriſt will not drinke this <hi>new wine</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone; he is not, will not be ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unleſſe his Saints partake with him: Thus he is brought in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170076:52"/>himſelfe to his Church in the place fore-named, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.1. <hi>I am come into my garden, my ſiſter, my ſpouſe, I have ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered my myrrhe with my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, I have eaten my hony combe with my hony, I have dranke my wine with my milk; eate O friends, drinke, drinke abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly O beloved.]</hi> Thus doth the Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> call his Church to communicate with him, as in his Kingdom of <hi>Grace</hi> here, ſo of <hi>Glory</hi> hereafter, where entering into his <hi>Garden,</hi> his heavenly <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> he doth as <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaketh of himſelfe <hi>Job</hi> 31.17.) <hi>not eat his morſell by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe alone,</hi> or drink his wine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, ingroſſing that heavenly glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to himſelfe, but he calleth his Saints and Angells to the partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of it. This is that which he makes promiſe of to his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19. where when
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170076:53"/>
                     <hi>Peter</hi> (ſpeaking in the name of the reſt (as often on other occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons he doth) demands of his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> what recompence they ſhould have for that love and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect which they had ſhown un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, in forſaking al for his ſake, he receiveth this anſwer from him (ver. 28.) <hi>Verily, I ſay unto you, that yee which have followed me in the regeneration, when the Son of man ſhall ſit on the throne of his glory; yee alſo ſhall ſit upon twelve thrones judging the twelve Tribes of Iſrael.]</hi> They ſhould be ſharers with their Maſter in his glory, when he ſhould ſit as a <hi>King</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Throne, they ſhould ſit as his <hi>Peeres</hi> about him; when he ſhould ſit as <hi>Lord Cheife Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> upon the <hi>Bench,</hi> they ſhould ſit as his <hi>Juſtices,</hi> as his <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſors.</hi> To the like purpoſe is that other promiſe. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.28,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170076:53"/>29. where our Saviour, to take his Apoſtles off from that vaine contention of theirs about a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall ſuperiority, a ſecular pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy; hee tels them that in as much as they had been partners with him in his <hi>Sufferings,</hi> and had hitherto owned him in his worſt condition, therefore they ſhould alſo communicate with him in his <hi>glory, [I appoint unto you a Kingdome, as my Father hath appointed unto me, that yee may eate and drinke at my Table in my Kingdome, &amp;c.]</hi> Thus ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had communion with him upon earth, he promiſeth them that they ſhould have communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with him in heaven. A <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe</hi> which in effect ſpeaketh the ſame thing with this here in the Text; where their Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter eating and drinking with them in the Sacrament of his <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> tels them, that one day, hee
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170076:54"/>would <hi>drinke that wine new</hi> with them, have a ſweet and bleſſed communion with them in the Kingdome of his Father, whereof that <hi>Sacramental Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> was a <hi>Repreſentation</hi> and a <hi>Pledge;</hi> this he promiſeth to his Apoſtles.</p>
                  <p>And what hee promiſeth to them, the like (for ſubſtance) ſhall he performe to all who have a like communion with him: even to all true <hi>beleevers,</hi> ſuch as here follow him, by <hi>profeſſion</hi> and <hi>imitation;</hi> they ſhall bee with him; <hi>where I am, there ſhall alſo my ſervant be,</hi> Joh. 12.26. This was a branch of his laſt <hi>Will,</hi> as he declares it, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.24. <hi>Father, I will that they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo whom thou haſt given mee</hi> (given to beleeve on me, as the 20. ver. explaines it) <hi>be with me where I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> that they may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold my glory]</hi> I, and not only
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170076:54"/>
                     <hi>behold</hi> it, but partake in it; <hi>The glory which thou haſt given me, I have given them</hi> (ſo we have it ver. 22.) That glory and happineſſe which God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had by promiſe inſured upon his Son Chriſt, by a like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe Chriſt maketh it over to all true beleevers, eſtating it upon them. And giving them a <hi>title</hi> to it here, he will put them into the actuall and full poſſeſſion of it hereafter. <hi>Come yee bleſſed of my Father, inherit the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome prepared for you from the foundation of the world, Matth.</hi> 25.34 Such a bleſſed Communion ſhall they have with Chriſt in heaven, who have here a ſpirituall communion with him upon earth.</p>
                  <p>Queſt.
<note place="margin">Celeſtiall communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on begun at the day of death.</note> 
                     <hi>But when ſhall they have this communion?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> I anſwer, The begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning hereof ſhall be at the day
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170076:55"/>of death. <hi>To day ſhalt thou be with me in paradiſe,</hi> ſaith our <hi>Saviour</hi> to the <hi>penitent theef,</hi> Luke 23.43. promiſing to meet with him in a place of reſt and happineſs; whether his ſoul was tranſlated upon the diſſolution and ſeparation of it from the Body. Thus it is ſaid of <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> that dying, he was forthwith <hi>carried by the Angels into</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams <hi>boſome,</hi> Luk. 16.22. his ſoul (his better part) was conveyed <hi>in receſſum quietis aeternae,</hi> into the retiring place of eternal reſt in Heaven, where he ſhould have communion with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> the Father of the faithful, and with other Saints and Angels. Here beginneth that <hi>bleſſed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> which the Saints ſhal have with <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Upon their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution they ſhall thenceforth be with him, beholding, enjoying him, and haing enjoyed of him.
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170076:55"/>
                     <hi>I deſire to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt,</hi> Phil. 1.23.</p>
                  <p>But the <hi>perfection</hi> hereof is reſerved to another day,
<note place="margin">Perfected at the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection.</note> the <hi>laſt day,</hi> the day of the general re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection and judgement, when the <hi>bodies</hi> of Gods Saints being raiſed out of their duſt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>united to their glorified <hi>ſpirits,</hi> ſhall be made joynt partakers of eternal glory and happineſs with <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Now ſhall this their bleſſed communion be at the <hi>full,</hi> which was before but in the <hi>change;</hi> and hereupon it is, that our Saviour here in the Text referreth this his <hi>drinking of this new wine</hi> with his Apoſtles unto that day, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>until that day,</hi> the day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is frequently in Scripture by way of eminency ſo called <hi>[That day.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>That day.</hi>
                     </note>] <hi>But the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren are not in darkneſs, that [that day] ſhould evertake you
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170076:56"/>as a theif,</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle to his <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> 1 Theſ. 5.4. ſpeaking of <hi>the day of the Lord,</hi> (as the ſecond verſe explains it) the day of his coming to judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>He ſhall come to be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in his Saints, and to be admired in all them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve [in that day]</hi> (ſith the ſame Apoſtle,) 2 Theſ. 1.10. <hi>I know whom I have beleeved</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and I am perſwaded that he is able to keep that which I have committed unto him againſt [that day.]</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12. And again, <hi>Hence forth is laid up for me a crown of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; which the Lord the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Judge ſhall give unto me at [that day.]</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. meaning, the time of Chriſts ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond coming, his coming to judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
<note place="margin">So called by way of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>minency.</note> which is called <hi>That day</hi> (as I ſaid) by way of excellency, as being the moſt remarkable
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170076:56"/>day, the <hi>laſt</hi> and <hi>great</hi> day: A day full of <hi>glory</hi> to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> of <hi>joy</hi> to the <hi>godly,</hi> of <hi>ſorrow</hi> to the <hi>wicked.</hi> A day which ſhall ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low up all days; after which there ſhall be no more viciſſitudes, and ſucceſſions of days and nights; but one perpetual <hi>day</hi> for the righteous, for whom <hi>light is ſown</hi> (as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> hath it. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 97.11.) One perpetual <hi>night</hi> for the ſinners and ungodly, who are <hi>children of the night,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.5. And at this day it is, that our Saviour here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth to <hi>drink this wine new</hi> with his Apoſtles, becauſe then, and not till then, he ſhould have a full communion with them, and they with him in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of glory. So is that fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named place moſt fitly and genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inely to be underſtood, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.28. <hi>Ye which have follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me in the Regeneration, where
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170076:57"/>the Son of Man ſhall ſit in the throne of his glory, ye alſo ſhall ſit upon twelve thrones,</hi> &amp;c.] Where thoſe words <hi>[In the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation]</hi> are more fitly refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto the latter part of the verſe, then to the former (as <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za</hi> and <hi>Grotius</hi> note upon it) as pointing at the day of the <hi>general Reſurrection,</hi> which ſhall be a day of <hi>renovation;</hi> when there ſhall be <hi>new Heavens, and a new Earth</hi> (as St. <hi>Peter</hi> tells us) 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13. and a general <hi>reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of all things</hi> (as he alſo ſaith of it) <hi>Acts</hi> 3.21. This time our Saviour there calleth <hi>the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, becauſe then the <hi>ſons of God</hi> ſhall be, as it were, <hi>begotten again</hi> the ſecond time; being here <hi>begotten to a lively hope</hi> (as the ſame Apoſtle hath it, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3.) they ſhall there be put into the actual and full poſſeſſion of the thing hoped
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170076:57"/>for, <hi>Receiving the end of their faith, the ſalvation of their Souls,</hi> (as it there followeth, <hi>verſ.</hi> 9.) Then ſhall they <hi>ſit</hi> with Jeſus Chriſt, having a full communion with him; then ſhall be that great and ſolemn <hi>feaſt</hi> of which our Saviour ſpeaketh, <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.11. When, <hi>Many ſhall come from the Eaſt, and from the Weſt, and ſhall ſit down with</hi> Abraham, <hi>and</hi> Iſaac, <hi>and</hi> Jacob, <hi>in the Kingdom of God.</hi> Gods Saints ſhall be gathered from all quarters of the world, and brought to that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that <hi>Caenaculum,</hi> that <hi>large up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per room</hi> (poſſibly repreſented by that, wherein our Saviour cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated the Paſſover, <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.12.) The heavenly <hi>Gueſt-chamber,</hi> where they ſhall have a ſweet communion with Jeſus Chriſt, and one with another. Then ſhall be that <hi>great Supper,</hi> the laſt
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170076:58"/>
                     <hi>marriage Supper of the Lamb,</hi> (of which, that mentioned <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.9. ſhall be a <hi>praeludium</hi>) when he ſhall drink this <hi>new wine</hi> (of which, not improbably that <hi>new wine</hi> which he made of water, at the marriage in <hi>Cana</hi> of <hi>Galilee</hi> was a Type,) with all thoſe who have here had a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual communion with him upon Earth.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>And why will he thus drink this new wine with them?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Why Chriſt will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate his glory to his Saintes.</note> 
                     <hi>Thus make them partakers of this glory and happineſs?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this I may anſwer. Firſt, This will he do to them, becauſe they are his <hi>favorites;</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> even as King <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> going to the <hi>banquet of Wine,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">They are his favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites.</note> which <hi>Eſther</hi> had prepared for him, taketh <hi>Haman</hi> along with him, being his ſpecial favorit, <hi>Eſth.</hi> 5.5. Such were the Apoſtles to Chriſt, being upon earth; and ſuch are
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170076:58"/>all true <hi>beleevers</hi> to him, being in Heaven: All <hi>Friends. Ye are my friends, if ye do whatſoever I command you,</hi> John 15.14. All <hi>Favorites.</hi> The people upon whom Jeſus Chriſt hath ſet a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar love, (<hi>who hath loved us, and waſhed us from our ſins in his own blood,</hi> Rev. 1.5.) whom he hath taken into a nearer rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to himſelf, then others; they are his <hi>Brethren, and Siſters, and Mother, Matth.</hi> 12.50. And upon this account it is, that he calleth and bringeth them to this <hi>banquet of wine,</hi> to drink this new wine with them.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Whileſt Jeſus Chriſt thus honoreth and glorifieth,
<note place="margin">Chriſt honored and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in his Saints.</note> them he himſelf is honored and <hi>glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in them</hi> and by them. So much we may learn from the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10. where ſpeaking of Chriſt, and his ſecond coming, he ſaith, <hi>He ſhall come to be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170076:59"/>in his Saints, and to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired in all them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve.</hi> Marke it. At this day Chriſt ſhall be <hi>glorified,</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in himſelfe, but alſo in his Saints; whoſe glory, as it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from him, ſo it redown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth alſo to him, and reflecteth upon him, ſo as he is thereby made more glorious; this grace and goodneſſe which he exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth upon them in ſo glorious a manner, being matter of everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing admiration to all that behold it: Even as the glory of the <hi>Court</hi> is the honor of the <hi>King.</hi> Thus the glory of the Saints is the glory of Chriſt, whoſe members they are.</p>
                  <p>And <hi>their joy is his joy;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Saints joy Chriſts joy.</note> ſo he calleth it, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.13. <hi>Theſe things ſpake I in the world, that they might have my joy ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled in them.] [my Joy]</hi> ſo he calleth their joy, (as for other reaſons, ſo), becauſe he rejoyceth
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170076:59"/>in the welfare and happineſſe of his people. Their joy ſhall bee his joy; Even as their ſufferings upon earth are his ſufferings. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, (as <hi>Paul</hi> calleth them, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.24.) [the Remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders] <hi>That which is behind of the afflictions of Chriſt;</hi> Even ſo their <hi>joyes</hi> are his <hi>joyes;</hi> which ſhall not bee fulfilled without them. Whence it is that the Church is called his <hi>fulneſſe,</hi> Epheſ. 1.23. <hi>The fulneſſe of him, that filleth all in all.</hi> Such is the love of Chriſt to his. Church, that though hee have a <hi>fulneſſe</hi> in himſelfe, and that not <hi>repletive</hi> onely, but <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſive</hi> alſo, communicating of his fulneſſe to others, not receiving any thing from them, yet he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counteth himſelfe defective, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he have his Church joyned to him, and made partakers of the ſame glory with him. But I
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170076:60"/>ſhall no longer dwell upon do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinall <hi>Illuſtration.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That which now remaines is practicall <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Applica∣tion. </seg>
                     </label> which I ſhall direct onely two wayes, by way of <hi>Conſolation, Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Uſe</hi> 1. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>1</label> By way of <hi>Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſuch as have communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with Chriſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth.</note> So our Saviour himſelfe here intends what he ſaith to his Apoſtles, that it might be as a <hi>Cordiall,</hi> firſt to <hi>himſelfe,</hi> then to <hi>them.</hi> To <hi>himſelfe,</hi> to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then his approaching <hi>Paſſion;</hi> to <hi>them,</hi> to comfort them concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his departing from them: And both theſe waies let it bee uſefull unto us; I mean ſuch, and onely ſuch as have communion with Jeſus Chriſt.
<note place="margin">In reſpect of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, a Cordial a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. or fears.</note> Being in our meaſure ſuch, now take this,</p>
                  <p n="1">1 As a <hi>Cordiall</hi> againſt <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> and <hi>imminent, felt</hi> or <hi>feared Tentations.</hi> In this caſe let Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians look beyond the preſent;
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170076:60"/>their preſent ſufferings or feares, ſetting before them this <hi>cup,</hi> this cup of <hi>new wine,</hi> prepared in heaven for them, after they have finiſhed their ſuffering worke. So did our bleſſed Saviour here, apprehending that <hi>bitter cup</hi> coming towards him, which he was to drink in his <hi>paſſion,</hi> he ſets before him this <hi>cup,</hi> this <hi>ſweet cup,</hi> which he ſhould drinke of in his <hi>exaltation.</hi> This is that which the Apoſtle tels us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2. where ſpeaking of Chriſt, and his exemplary patience in his ſufferings, he ſaith, that <hi>for the joy which was ſet before him, he indured the croſſe, and deſpiſed the ſhame,</hi> &amp;c.] Thus did he drown all his ſorrowes and fears in this <hi>cup of new wine,</hi> in the apprehenſion of that heavenly glory which waited for him after his ſuffering worke was over. In this way it was (as is moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170076:61"/>conjectured) that the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of God is ſaid to have <hi>ſtrengthened him</hi> in his <hi>Agony,</hi> Luk. 22.43. <hi>And there appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto him an Angell from heaven ſtrengthning him.]</hi> This he did, not by infuſing, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating to him any power or vertue,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chriſtus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim deſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis in ſe habitantis virtute, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manaeque naturae re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lictus, ac proinde,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus habuit Angelorum ſolatio.</hi> Gro. Annot. in Lu. 22.43. New wine for heavy hearts.</note> but by preſenting unto his <hi>humanity</hi> (his <hi>divinity</hi> being for the preſent aſleep, and the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of it for the time ſuſpended, (as <hi>Grotius</hi> there ingeniouſly explains it) the certain aſſurance of a ſpeedy victory, and inſuing glory. And in the like way let me (as an Angell, and Miniſter of Chriſt) ſtrengthen your hearts againſt what ever tentations and ſufferings yee are ſubject unto, <hi>viz.</hi> by ſetting this <hi>new wine</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you.</p>
                  <p>So <hi>Salomon</hi> (or rather <hi>Bath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheba,</hi> for he learned that leſſon from his <hi>Mother,</hi> as in the firſt
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170076:61"/>verſe of the Chapter he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth) adviſeth in the place forenamed, <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.6, 7. <hi>Give ſtrong drink to him that is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to periſh, and wine to thoſe that bee of heavy hearts; let him drinke and forget his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, and remember his miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry no more.]</hi> And this counſell ſhall I here lay hold upon, mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing uſe of it in a ſpirituall way, giving this <hi>new wine</hi> to thoſe that are of <hi>heavy hearts,</hi> preſenting unto dejected ſpirits in their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſolate condition this <hi>cup of conſolation,</hi> which I ſhal deſire all ſuch not only to <hi>taſt,</hi> but to <hi>drink</hi> of, and that a hearty draught, to <hi>ſit at it.</hi> So doe <hi>Wine bibbers</hi> uſe to doe at their wine, againſt whom the Prophet denounceth that woe, which I ſhall deſire all ſuch <hi>Good-fellowes</hi> to take notice of, <hi>Iſa</hi> 5.11. <hi>Woe unto them that riſe up early in the morning,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170076:62"/>that they may follow ſtrong drink, that continue till night, till wine inflame them.]</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chriſtians to ſit at this wine.</note> They <hi>ſit</hi> at the wine; the like let Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans do at <hi>this wine;</hi> in the drinking whereof, there is no fear of exceſs; <hi>ſit at it,</hi> continue by it, I mean, by <hi>Divine meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and <hi>ſerious contemplation,</hi> often ſetting before them the <hi>joy</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> of Heaven, which God hath prepared for his Saints and ſervants, after that they have ſuffered a while. Here (it may be) they meet with many a bitter draught, they have <hi>their afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and their miſery, their worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, and their gall,</hi> (as the Church deſcribes her ſad condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>Babylon, Lam.</hi> 3.19.) But let them remember there is <hi>wine, new wine</hi> laid up in Heaven for them.
<note place="margin">A Cordial for ſuch as ſuffer for Chriſt.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>And how ſhould the thought hereof comfort and ſtrengthen
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170076:62"/>the hearts of all the <hi>ſons</hi> and <hi>daughters</hi> of <hi>Sion,</hi> in the midſt of what ever ſufferings? eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, if they be <hi>ſufferings for Chriſt.</hi> Now let them know, that drinking of his <hi>Cup</hi> here, they ſhall drink of it hereafter. Drinking of his <hi>bitter cup,</hi> they ſhall drink of his <hi>ſweet cup;</hi> drinking of his <hi>Vinegar,</hi> his old and ſowre wine here, they ſhall drink with him of his <hi>new</hi> and <hi>ſweet wine</hi> another day. Having thus communion with him in his <hi>ſufferings</hi> upon earth, they ſhall have communion with him in his <hi>glory</hi> and <hi>happineſs</hi> in Heaven. <hi>Ye are they</hi> (ſaith our Saviour to his Apoſtles) <hi>who have continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with me in my temptations: Therefore I appoint unto you a Kingdom, as my Father hath appointed me, that ye may eat and drink at my table in my Kingdom,</hi> Luke 22.28, 29.
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170076:63"/>Thus being ſharers with Chriſt in his <hi>Croſs,</hi> they ſhall be alſo in his <hi>Crown. If we ſuffer with him, we ſhall alſo be glorified with him; reign with him,</hi> Rom. 8.17. 2 Tim. 2.12.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſtians!</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chriſtians to have an eye to the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of reward.</note> Be ye more in the thought of this, feeling your hearts oppreſſed with the weight of <hi>temporal ſufferings,</hi> do but caſt the <hi>glory of Heaven</hi> into the contrary ballance againſt them. So did <hi>Moſes,</hi> of whom the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle tells us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.26. That <hi>he eſteemed the reproach of Chriſt</hi> (for Chriſts ſake) <hi>greater riches then the treaſures of</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt; <hi>for he had an eye to the recompence of reward;</hi> not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the earthly <hi>Canaan</hi> (as <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> would have it) but to the heavenly, and to the <hi>glory</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
                  <p>This is the Chriſtians <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, of which the ſame Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170076:63"/>ſpeaketh in the Chapter fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going, Verſ. 35. <hi>Caſt not away your confidence, which hath great recompence of reward;</hi> not onely <hi>temporal,</hi> but <hi>eternal.</hi> And this it was, which <hi>Moſes</hi> there had an eye at, the reward of eternal life. This it was, that he put in the ſcale againſt all his ſufferings: the like do we; which doing, we ſhall finde this infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preponderating and weighing down the other. So it did at <hi>Pauls</hi> beam. <hi>I reckon</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that the ſufferings of this preſent life are not worthy to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the glory which ſhall be revealed in us.</hi> So it is. The <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the <hi>ſufferings,</hi> the Martyrdoms of this preſent life; be hey never ſo many, never ſo great, yet they are not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, they hold no proportion with the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence of reward,</hi> the glory of Heaven: The one being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratively
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170076:64"/>
                     <hi>light,</hi> the other <hi>pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous;</hi> the one <hi>momentany,</hi> the other <hi>eternal.</hi> So the Apoſtle weighing them in the ballance of the Sanctuary, ſets his <hi>Tekel</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the former, in that elegant <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantiôſis</hi> of his, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Our light affliction, which is but for a moment, worketh for us a far more exceeding, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal weight of glory.</hi> Ever then let this be in our right eye. In imitation of our heavenly pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern, ſet we this <hi>joy</hi> before us: And herewith ſtay our hearts againſt whatever apprehenſions, or fears.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yed,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A Cordial in the laſt agony.</note> 
                     <hi>even of death it ſelf.</hi> That is a <hi>Cup</hi> which we muſt all drink of, ſooner or later; and to fleſh and blood it is a <hi>bitter cup. The bitterneſs of death is paſt</hi> (ſaith <hi>Agag,</hi> when he thought to have eſcaped with his life,) 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.32. <hi>I finde more bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170076:64"/>then death</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> of the deceitful woman,) <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.26. <hi>Death is a bitter cup;</hi> it will be found ſo to thoſe who have nothing to ſweeten their mouths with. To allay the bitterneſs of it, ſweeten it with this <hi>new wine,</hi> the apprehenſion of heavenly glory; which being taſted of, apprehended by Faith, will be of ſoveraign uſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the heart, and bear up the Spirit in the midſt of this laſt <hi>agony.</hi> Of ſuch uſe was it to our <hi>Saviour,</hi> and of ſuch uſe let it be to all that are his.</p>
                  <p>Thus in the midſt of what ever <hi>conflicts</hi> here we meet with in our warfare upon earth, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber we what is laid up in Heaven for us; what through Chriſt (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his, his Subjects, his Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,) we may certainly expect and look for, when we have fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed our courſe.</p>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:170076:65"/>
                  <p>It was the ſpeech of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> General, wherewith he is ſaid to have encouraged his Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, being to engage in a hazard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous battel; <hi>So dine ye this day</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>as remembring that ye are to ſup in another world.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Muſcul. ad Text.</note> This Speech <hi>Muſculus</hi> (writing upon the Text) taketh notice of, as a paſſage which hath been looked upon by many, as worthy to be remembred by Chriſtians. But how much more (ſaith he) is this ſentence of our Saviour here to his Apoſtles, worthy to be recommended to them, and inculcated upon them? Where he maketh promiſe to thoſe who ſhall ſtick cloſe to him, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him (as his Apoſtles had done) that they ſhall ſup with him in another world; have a ſweet communion with him, drinking of this <hi>new wine</hi> with him in the Kingdom of his Father.
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170076:65"/>Thus make we uſe of this in our own perſonal <hi>tentations</hi> and <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And (ſecondly) make uſe of it in reference to others.
<note place="margin">In reſpect of others. A Cordial for ſuch as are to part with their neareſt and dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> When we are to part with our neareſt, and deareſt <hi>relations, Husbands</hi> to part with their <hi>Wives, Wives</hi> with their <hi>Husbands; Parents</hi> with their <hi>Children,</hi> or <hi>Children</hi> with their <hi>Parents:</hi> Theſe are to be taken from us by death, who while they lived, were the delight of our eyes, and the joy of our hearts, among the cheif of our earthly comforts.</p>
                  <p>This is a time wherein com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort is very ſeaſonable. Now a <hi>cup of conſolation</hi> would do well. Such a cuſtom there was amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> (as we may learn from the Prophet <hi>Jeremy, Jer.</hi> 16.7. where ſpeaking of thoſe calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous times which ſhould come upon that Nation, wherein all
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170076:66"/>neighborly offices of love and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect one to another, ſhould be wholly neglected and laid aſide, among other things, he ſaith, <hi>That they ſhould not give the cup of conſolation to their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren for their Father, or for their Mother,)</hi> when any of their friends were in heavineſs for the loſs of thoſe who were near and dear to them, not to put them to the trouble and charge of a feaſt (as the cuſtom now a days is,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Longe ſecùs quâm apud nos in uſu eſt, ubi vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duae morte conjugum graviter afflictae menſam vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinis, &amp; cognatis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firuunt.</hi> Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright. Com. in Prov. 31.6, 7.</note> not ſo fitly and approvedly, as our reverend <hi>Cartwright</hi> notes it, writing upon <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.6, 7.) but either to invite them to their Houſes, or elſe to ſend in to them proviſions of meat and drink, that ſo by eating and drinking with them, they might help them the better to digeſt, and put over their grief. This was that which the Prophet there cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the <hi>cup of conſolation.</hi> Such
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170076:66"/>a <hi>cup</hi> our bleſſed Saviour here giveth to his Apoſtles. His de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture being now at hand, and he taking his leave of them, leaveth this <hi>conſolation</hi> with them; that however he and they ſhould part for a time, yet it ſhould be but for a time. There ſhould come a day when they ſhould meet again, and then they ſhould drink a <hi>better cup,</hi> have a better communion together, then now they had. And the like <hi>cup of conſolation</hi> let me this day put into the hands of all ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, as either at preſent are, or (how ſoon, you know not) may be in the like condition; whom God hath called, or ſhall call to part with your deareſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations (as a parting there muſt be:) Know you, and conſider, that this is but a parting for a time. This I ſpeak in reference to ſuch, as you have comfortable
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170076:67"/>hopes of, that they <hi>are dead in the Lord.</hi> Indeed, as for others, ſuch as <hi>live and die without hope;</hi> to part with them, is a ſad parting: But being ſuch, ſuch as are <hi>faln aſleep in Chriſt;</hi> now know, that your parting with them, is but for a time, not for ever. <hi>Though they ſhall not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to you, yet you ſhall go to them</hi> (as <hi>David</hi> ſaid of his <hi>childe,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.23.) So as you and they ſhall have a meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Heaven, where you ſhall both have a ſweet communion with <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and (ſo far forth as may make for your mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al happineſs) one with another; drinking of this <hi>new wine,</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>2</label> enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe <hi>joyes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to make ſure our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Chriſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth.</note> which ſhall never more know what any mixture of ſorrow meaneth. This by way of <hi>Conſolation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Which that we may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly apply, and bring home
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170076:67"/>to our ſelves, be we exhorted (in the ſecond place) every of us, to endeavor to make this ſure to our ſelves, That we be (as <hi>Paul</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth beleevers, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.8.) <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the promiſe;</hi> ſuch as to whom this <hi>promiſe</hi> belongs. Who they are, I have hinted to you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, in laying down the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> viz. <hi>Such as have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Jeſus Chriſt upon Earth.</hi> Such onely ſhall have communion with him in <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> Every of us then have an eye to this.</p>
                  <p>And here content not we our ſelves with an <hi>outward,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenting our ſelves with viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</note> 
                     <hi>viſible communion:</hi> Not, but that alſo we muſt have a regard unto this, to have an <hi>outward communion</hi> with Jeſus Chriſt, to own him, follow him in a viſible profeſſion of his Name,
<note place="margin">Which yet is not to be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected.</note> and to meet him in his Ordinances; as in <hi>hearing</hi> of his Word, ſo in partaking in
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170076:68"/>his <hi>Supper</hi> to <hi>eat</hi> and <hi>drink</hi> with him at his <hi>Table.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which <hi>Ordinance</hi> Chriſtians ought the rather to have regard unto, and make uſe of, in as much as it is both a <hi>ſign</hi> and a <hi>pledge</hi> of their heavenly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.
<note place="margin">Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</note> Such is this <hi>Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal communion</hi> in the Supper.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> A <hi>ſign</hi> repreſenting it. So it doth,
<note place="margin">A ſign re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> and that moſt lively; ſpecially as that Ordinance is now adminiſtred unto you, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by you in this Congregation; where your <hi>ſitting at the Table,</hi> and there eating and drinking of the Sacramental Bread and Wine together,
<note place="margin">Sitting at the Table, a Myſtical ceremony, repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Saints in Heaven.</note> carrieth with it a more lively repreſentation and reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of that <hi>heavenly commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> which one day you hope to have with Jeſus Chriſt, and with his Saints and Angels, then any other form or manner of Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration doth, or can do. So
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170076:68"/>much is not obſcurely inſinuated unto us in thoſe <hi>expreſſions,</hi> which our bleſſed Saviour is pleaſed to make uſe of in deſcribing and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth that heavenly commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; which he doth by <hi>ſitting,</hi> Matth. 8.11. <hi>Many ſhall come from the Eaſt, and from the Weſt, and ſhall ſit down with</hi> Abraham, <hi>and</hi> Iſaac, <hi>and</hi> Jacob, <hi>in the Kingdom of God.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Accumbent, ſit down.</hi> A metaphor taken from <hi>feaſts,</hi> or <hi>banquets,</hi> where men of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent conditions <hi>ſit down</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo having a civil communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one with another. So do the <hi>gueſts,</hi> whileſt the <hi>ſervitors</hi> ſtand by; as the ſtory tell us <hi>Martha</hi> did, while <hi>Lazarus,</hi> with the reſt, <hi>ſate at table</hi> with our Saviour, <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.2. And ſo again, <hi>by eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and drinking at the Table,</hi> Luke 22.30. <hi>I appoint unto you a Kingdom,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>That ye may
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170076:69"/>eat and drink at my Table.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, At my Table. An expreſſion queſtionleſs derived from his <hi>laſt Supper,</hi> which he had then adminiſtred; where his Apoſtles <hi>ſate down</hi> with him, <hi>eating and drinking at his ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi> Thus they then celebrated the <hi>Paſſover;</hi> not <hi>ſtanding</hi> (which geſture was appropriated unto that <hi>firſt Paſſover</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> becauſe they were to <hi>eat it in haſte,</hi> (as <hi>Moſes</hi> tells them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.11.) but <hi>ſitting,</hi> their ordinary <hi>table geſture,</hi> as the Evangeliſts <hi>Matthew</hi> and <hi>Mark</hi> both expreſs it, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.20. <hi>Mark</hi> 14.18. And in the ſame poſture they celebrated the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſtical Supper; ſitting, and eating, and drinking at the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi> Which was to them a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of that <hi>heavenly communion,</hi> which there he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth they ſhould have with
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170076:69"/>him in <hi>Heaven;</hi> ſhadowing it out not onely in the <hi>actions</hi> of <hi>eating</hi> and <hi>drinking;</hi> but alſo in the <hi>poſture</hi> of <hi>ſitting,</hi> and eating and drinking <hi>at the table.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A geſture not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to any juſt excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> Which I deſire it may be the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther taken notice of, for the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of ſuch as make a ſcruple of the like manner of adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at this day: Which, being ſo conform and agreeable to the <hi>Primitive pattern,</hi> cannot, I am ſure, upon any juſt ground be quarrelled with.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> As this <hi>Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal communion</hi> is a <hi>ſign,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion a pledge of celeſtial.</note> ſo a <hi>pledge</hi> of the heavenly commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. As a ſign <hi>repreſenting</hi> it, ſo a pledge <hi>ſealing,</hi> aſſuring it to all the worthy receivers of that Sacrament. And upon this dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble account (amongſt others) it ought not to be neglected, but conſcientiouſly attended upon, where it is according to Chriſts Inſtitution held forth.</p>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:170076:70"/>
                  <p>But Chriſtians may not reſt here,
<note place="margin">External communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on not to be reſted in.</note> in ſuch an <hi>external com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</hi> This <hi>Judas</hi> had; he followed his <hi>Maſter in an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward profeſsion,</hi> as well, as the reſt of the <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> he heard his <hi>word;</hi> he participated with him in the <hi>Paſſover,</hi> and for ought I know, in the <hi>Supper</hi> alſo. Yet had he nothing to do with this promiſe; being firſt a <hi>Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> to his Maſter, and after, his own <hi>executioner,</hi> he went <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>to his own place,</hi> (as St. <hi>Luke</hi> tells us, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.25.) that is, to that <hi>Hell,</hi> which was a place more fit for him, then that wherein he was among the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles; and a place to which, for his treachery and perfidiouſneſs, he was by God juſtly deſigned, (as that Text is commonly (and I think properly) expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.)</p>
                  <p>See then that we go further,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170076:70"/>that we have an <hi>inward, ſpiritual,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Inward, ſpiritual communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be ſought after. Rom. 6.5.</note> 
                     <hi>inviſible, myſtical communion</hi> with the <hi>Lord Jeſus.</hi> That, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>ingrafted</hi> into him, not onely <hi>Sacramentally</hi> (as all perſons baptized are) but <hi>really,</hi> and truly united to him by <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>love,</hi> we be made partakers of his <hi>Spirit,</hi> which may transform us into his <hi>Image.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eph. 3.17.</note> That <hi>Chriſt may dwell in our hearts,</hi> being preſent in us by the influence of his Grace and Spirit; commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating to us the vertue of his <hi>death</hi> and <hi>reſurrection,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Phil. 3.10.</note> whereby we may be inabled to die unto <hi>ſin,</hi> and to live unto <hi>righteouſneſs;</hi> ſhewing forth his <hi>vertues,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing his <hi>life,</hi> imitating his <hi>obedience,</hi> in doing and ſuffering the will of our heavenly Father; not onely <hi>hearing,</hi> but <hi>receiving his words</hi> (as the Apoſtles are ſaid to do, <hi>John</hi> 17.8.) not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eating of his <hi>bread,</hi> and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170076:71"/>of his <hi>cup</hi> in the Sacrament, (which many do upon earth, who ſhall never eat or drink at his table in Heaven) but that we eat his <hi>fleſh,</hi> and drink his <hi>blood;</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the merits of his death un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our ſelves, unto our juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; looking up to him, and by faith hanging upon him for a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual ſupply of his <hi>Spirit,</hi> whereby we may be <hi>ſtrengthned in the inward man,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eph. 3.16. 2 Cor. 3.18.</note> 
                     <hi>and changed from glory to glory;</hi> growing from <hi>grace to grace,</hi> until we <hi>ſhall all come in the unity of the Faith, and knowledge of the Son of God, unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.13.) Having ſuch a <hi>communion</hi> with this our bleſſed Lord and Saviour here, in his Kingdom of <hi>grace</hi> upon earth, we ſhall have a <hi>bleſſed Communion</hi> with him in
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170076:71"/>his Kingdom of <hi>glory</hi> in <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> where we ſhall <hi>drink of this fruit of the Vine new</hi> with him to all eternity. Which honor and happineſs may <hi>he</hi> vouchſafe to every of us, <hi>To whom with the Father, and the Holy Ghoſt, be praiſe and thanks giving now and for ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170076:72"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:170076:72"/>
                  <p>Acquaintance WITH GOD: THE Nature of it opened, The Practice Perſwaded, Incouraged, Directed, Cautioned. As it was lately delivered to the Church of God at <hi>Great Yarmouth.</hi> By <hi>John Brinſley,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpell there.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London</hi> Printed by <hi>R. I.</hi> for <hi>Tho. Newbery</hi> at the three golden Lyons in Cornhil.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170076:73"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:170076:73"/>
                  <head>To the right Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, the Lady ANNE WENTWORTH, at her houſe in <hi>Somerleyton,</hi> in the County of <hi>Suffolk.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> 
                     <hi>Can not, I may not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects which my ſelfe ſome years ſince found from your late ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured</hi> Husband, <hi>and your ſelfe; how, during my</hi> exile <hi>(in the late</hi> dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult times) <hi>from the</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:170076:74"/>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Great Yarmouth</note> 
                     <hi>place to which God firſt called, and hath ſince returned me, you were pleaſed to provide me a reſidence and ſubſiſtance in your neighboring</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">The Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land of Loving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note> Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos; <hi>where for ſome time I exerciſed my Miniſtery, firſt as a</hi> Teacher, <hi>in a</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Lownde</note> 
                     <hi>Village near you, and after as a</hi> Paſtor <hi>in the</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Somer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leyton.</note> 
                     <hi>place of your owne ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation. As a gratefull acknowledgement of that immerited favour (not having a better preſent) I doe here put this ſmall</hi> Tract <hi>into your</hi> Ladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips
<pb facs="tcp:170076:74"/>
                     <hi>hand. The</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject matter whereof <hi>(what ever the Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip be) is ſuch, as may deſerve a reception.</hi> Acquaintance with God, <hi>it is the cheif hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of the reaſonable creature. This, (I truſt) your Ladiſhip is not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether a stranger to. My deſire is, that you may grow up to a further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of this bleſsed famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arity. And to that end I ſhall crave from you a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious peruſal of this ſmal</hi> Manuall; <hi>wherein you
<pb facs="tcp:170076:75"/>ſhall find, as the</hi> Nature <hi>of this great Duty</hi> open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>ſo the</hi> Practice <hi>of it</hi> Incouraged, directed, Cautioned. <hi>May my labours in this way prove uſefull to your</hi> Ladiſhip, <hi>I ſhall look upon it as the beſt retribution that I am, or ever ſhall bee able to make you. In the deſires and hopes whereof, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly take my leave, reſting</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Ladiſhips Obliged to ſerve you in all Chriſtian Offices, JOHN BRINSLEY.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Yarmouth</hi> 
                        <date>14. <hi>July Anno.</hi> 1653.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:170076:75"/>
                  <head>Acquaintance with God.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Job 22.21.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Acquaint now thy ſelfe with him, and be at peace; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſhall good come unto thee.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this Verſe (as <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> looketh upon it) we have a briefe <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomie</hi> and <hi>Summary</hi> of all the <hi>Counſell</hi> and <hi>Comfort</hi> which the wiſe <hi>Temanite Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaz</hi> holdeth forth unto his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted friend <hi>Job</hi> in the latter part of this Chapter.
<note place="margin">Junii Ann. ad loc.</note> Mine eye at preſent is principally upon the former of theſe, <hi>Counſell;</hi> which,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:170076:76"/>ſetting aſide the miſtake in the <hi>perſonall Application</hi> of it, we ſhall finde in it ſelfe wholeſome, and ſoveraign.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Acquaint now thy ſelfe with him</hi>] that is, with the <hi>Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:</hi> ſo the 23. verſe maketh it out, with <hi>God.</hi> Where, before I come to the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of the <hi>Counſell,</hi> let me by the way take notice of that <hi>circumſtance,</hi> which I meet with in the Particle [<hi>Now.</hi>]</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Acquaint [Now] thy ſelfe.]</hi> The word in the originall is (<hi>Na</hi>)<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> which may bee tranſlated either <hi>quaeſe,</hi> or <hi>nune;</hi> either, <hi>I pray thee,</hi> or <hi>now.</hi> In the former ſenſe it is uſed often, as a particle of obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, intreating, and beſeeching one; So it is tranſlated in the verſe following: And ſo <hi>Tremel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> (with whom our former Tranſlation agrees) here renders it. <hi>Aſſueſce quaeſe. Acquaint thy ſelfe, I pray thee, with him.</hi>]</p>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:170076:76"/>
                  <p>Now, ſhall we ſo look upon it, then it denotes &amp; imports the <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection</hi> of the ſpeaker; who having before dealt ſomwhat harſhly and rigidly with his friend <hi>Job,</hi> now he changeth his note, ſpeaking to him in a more milde and gentle language, that ſo his former words might the rather take place with him, and be the better dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by him. To which end alſo he here intimates unto him the ſerious and earneſt deſire which he had of his good and welfare, that by hearkning to his advice, he might reap the comfort and benefit of it. [<hi>I pray thee.</hi>]</p>
                  <p>With ſuch <hi>affection</hi> ought Gods <hi>Interpreters,</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>
                     </label> his <hi>Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi> his <hi>Miniſters</hi> to ſpeake unto his people. How ever they are not to ſpare their ſins, but to deale plainly with them,
<note place="margin">Tit. 1.13.</note> 
                     <hi>rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king</hi> them, and that where need is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>cuttingly, ſharpely;</hi>
                     <pb n="122" facs="tcp:170076:77"/>ſetting their ſinnes in order before them, thundering out the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God againſt them in caſe they ſhall perſiſt in them (as <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liphaz</hi> here doth in the former part of this chapter) yet withall they are to deale lovingly and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionately with them, imitating the Phyſician, who wraps his bitter pils in Sugar; or gives his Patient ſome ſweet morſell after a diſtaſteful potion: Thus are they to ſweeten tart Reprehenſions, with milde and affectionate Inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuations; breathing love into the boſomes of thoſe whom they are inforced to deale harſhly with, making it manifeſt they deſire no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more then that their advice and counſel may bee accepted of them. To which end (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they may (as Gods <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers</hi> in an authoritative way command, yet) they are to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Suitors to them. As <hi>Paul</hi>
                     <pb n="123" facs="tcp:170076:77"/>ſaith to his <hi>Philemon</hi> ver. 8, 9. <hi>Though I might be much bold in Chriſt, to enjoyne thee that which is convenient; yet for loves ſake I rather beſeech thee.</hi>] Thus are the Miniſters of Chriſt to deale with thoſe committed to their charge, intreating, beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, what they might command: <hi>I beſeech you Brethren</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> to his <hi>Romans</hi>) chap. 12.1. <hi>As if God did beſeech you by us, we pray you in Chriſts ſtead, be yee reconciled to God,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.20. A language fit for a Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell <hi>Miniſter.</hi> But I ſhall not dwell upon it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Others (with whom our preſent Tranſlation goeth along) look upon it as an <hi>Adverb</hi> of <hi>Time, Nunc, Now acquaint thy ſelfe with him.</hi>] Take it ſo, it admits of a twofold reference, either to <hi>Jobs preſent condition,</hi> or to <hi>Eliphaz his foregoing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:170076:78"/>
                  <p n="1">1 To <hi>Jobs preſent condition,</hi> which was an afflicted ſtate, hee then lying under the hand of God, under many ſad and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous afflictions. In this condition <hi>Eliphaz</hi> may be conceived here to beſpeak him after this manner: [<hi>Now acquaint thy ſelfe with him.</hi>]</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Time of affliction is a proper time,</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>a fit ſeaſon for poor ſinners to come in unto God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Converſion and true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, which are never out of ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, are then very ſeaſonable. <hi>Come</hi> (ſaith the Church) <hi>and let us return unto the Lord, for he hath torn, and he will heale us: he hath ſmitten and he will bind us up.</hi>] Hoſ. 6.1. Not to come in unto God at ſuch a time, is a double iniquity, no ſmall aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of a former Rebellion. So the Lord chargeth it upon <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in that knowne place, <hi>Amos</hi> 4.
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:170076:78"/>where he repeats this as the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of his complaint,
<note place="margin">Amos 4. v. 6, 8, 9, 10, 11.</note> no leſs then five ſeveral times. I have done thus, and thus to you; ſmiting you with this judgement, and with that, But <hi>yet ye have not returned unto me, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Applic.</hi> Taking notice here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, let <hi>Eliphaz</hi> his (<hi>now</hi>) in this ſenſe take place with every of us, who in any degree are brought into <hi>Jobs</hi> condition.</p>
                  <p>Is it ſo, that the hand of God is out againſt us in what kinde ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be? Now, now acquaint our ſelves with him, and make peace. A proper time for ſuch a purpoſe. When the wrath and diſpleaſure of God is kindled againſt us, and breok forth upon us, then to ſeek unto God. <hi>In their affliction they will ſeek me early</hi> (or <hi>diligently,) Hoſea</hi> 5. <hi>ult.</hi> To this end, it is that God
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:170076:79"/>breaketh forth upon thoſe whom he hath a gracious purpoſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 14.</note> Even as <hi>Abſalom</hi> dealt with <hi>Joah,</hi> when he would not come at him, he ſets his field on fire to bring him to him. Thus dealeth God ſometimes with his own people; when they eſtrange themſelves from him, and other invitations take not place with them, he cauſeth the fire of his wrath to break forth upon them, by that means to bring them home to himſelf. Herein then let God have his end; which if we do, we ſhall have the comfort and benefit of it. <hi>Now acquaint thy ſelf with him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The other reference of this particle (<hi>Now</hi>) is to <hi>Eliphaz his foregoing diſcourſe.</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> In the verſes foregoing <hi>Eliphaz</hi> had been diſcourſing unto <hi>Job,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 24.5.</note> (as <hi>Paul</hi> did once unto <hi>Felix</hi>) of
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:170076:79"/>
                     <hi>judgement:</hi> Shewing what diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſters, what miſchiefs had befaln wicked and ungodly men, ſuch as had no regard to have any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with God, and to walk with him. <hi>Haſt thou marked the old way</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>which wicked men have trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den?</hi> Verſ. 15. (the <hi>old way,</hi> or <hi>the way of the old, viz.</hi> The old world before the flood, (as ſome expound it) <hi>which were cut down before the time, whoſe foundation was overflown with a flood,</hi> Verſ. 16. They were ſwept away with that univerſal deluge. Thus dealt God with them: And after the like manner he often dealeth with others, who walk in their ways. [<hi>The rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of them the fire conſumeth</hi> (ſaith the words before the Text) <hi>Verſ.</hi> 20. Such others as they were, God deſtroyeth, if not with <hi>water,</hi> yet with <hi>fire;</hi> which
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:170076:80"/>he doth ſometimes <hi>literally,</hi> as he did them of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah;</hi> oft times <hi>metaphorically,</hi> conſuming them by his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, his wrath breaking forth upon them like unto fire. Now ſeeing it is ſo, ſeeing this is Gods ordinary dealing with wicked men; <hi>Therefore,</hi> or <hi>Now ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint thy ſelf with him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Obſerv. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>Such uſe ought men to make of the judgements of God executed upon others.</hi> Judgements which they ſee, which they hear of, they are ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to be deterred from walking in wicked ways. <hi>Poena ad parvos, terror ad omnes.</hi> Some are puniſhed, that all may be warned. To this end, God requires that judgement ſhould be executed upon the preſumptuous ſinner in ſo ſevere and exemplary a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. <hi>That man ſhall
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:170076:80"/>die, Verſ.</hi> 12. Die without mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. And wherefore ſo? The reaſon followeth; <hi>And all the people ſhall hear, and fear, and do no more preſumptuouſly.</hi> And the like uſe ſhould men make of divine judgements executed upon wicked and ungodly men, whom God maketh ſpectacles of his vengeance and wrath. Seeing them, or hearing of them, they ſhould fear to ſin preſumptuouſly, not dare to go on in a courſe of ſin: But breaking off their ſins by repentance, they ſhould come in unto God, betaking themſelves to the working of righteouſneſs. <hi>When thy judgements are in the earth, the inhabitants of the world will learn righteouſneſs,</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>Iſai.</hi> 26.9. they will learn, that is, they do, or ought to do it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Applic.</hi> And this do we. None of us but have ſeen, or
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:170076:81"/>heard of terrible judgements executed upon preſumptuous ſinners; ſuch as have had no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to walk with God; how the fire of his wrath hath broke forth upon them in temporal plagues and puniſhments; ſo as they have been <hi>cut down before the time,</hi> taken away by untimely deaths, not <hi>living out half their days</hi> (as <hi>David</hi> ſaith of <hi>Bloody and deceitful men, Pſal.</hi> 55. <hi>laſt.) and their foundation hath been overflown with a flood.</hi>] God hath ſent ſome ſweeping judgements upon them; begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and making an end at once (as he threatens againſt the houſe of <hi>Ely,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.12.) Now let all theſe be as ſo many warning peeces unto us; teaching us to decline thoſe ways which they have trodden, that ſo we may never pledge them in that cup of wrath and vengeance which they
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:170076:81"/>have drunk of. <hi>Now acquaint thy ſelf with him,</hi> &amp;c.]</p>
                  <p>But I paſs from the <hi>circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> to the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of this counſel; wherein I ſhall take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of two things.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Of what is here <hi>impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> then what is <hi>expreſſed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. That which is <hi>implied,</hi> is, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>1</label> That <hi>wicked and ungodly men are eſtranged from God.</hi> So much this phraſe imports: To get acquaintance with one, it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports a foregoing ſtrangeneſs. And ſo much <hi>Eliphaz</hi> here intimates concerning <hi>Job,</hi> judging him to be ſuch a one, a wicked, and ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man, he looketh upon him as a <hi>ſtranger</hi> to God, one that had no <hi>acquaintance</hi> with him. And ſuch is the condition of all thoſe who are really ſuch, they are <hi>ſtrangers</hi> to God. So we finde them called, <hi>Joel</hi> 3.17. where the Prophet ſpeaking of the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:170076:82"/>
                     <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> the Church under the Goſpel, he ſaith, [<hi>She ſhall be holy, and there ſhall no ſtranger paſs thorow her any more;</hi>] that is, ſuch ſhall be the purity of the Church, as that there ſhall be no unclean, no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane perſon in it. So the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> expounds it, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 35.8. where holding forth the like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy, he ſaith [<hi>A high-way ſhall be there, and a way, and it ſhall be called the way of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; the unclean ſhall not paſs over it.</hi>] And Saint <hi>John</hi> more plainly, (if we ſhall underſtand that prophecy concerning the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> upon Earth, as very fitly we may) <hi>Revel.</hi> 21. laſt, <hi>There ſhall in no wiſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>enter into it any thing that defileth, neither whatſoever worketh abomination, &amp;c.</hi>] Such ſhall be the purity of the Church in the latter days, through
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:170076:82"/>the ſtrict exerciſe of <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> that no prophane perſon ſhall be admitted into the boſome of it, to have and hold communion with it. Lo, theſe are the <hi>ſtrangers</hi> which the Prophet <hi>Joel</hi> there ſpeaketh of; even all wicked and ungodly perſons, who are <hi>ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gens to God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Such they are, being firſt, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> 
                     <hi>born ſo. The wicked are eſtranged from the womb,</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt,) Pſal.</hi> 58.3. <hi>Being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienated from the life of God, through the ignorance that is in them, becauſe of the blindneſs of their minde</hi> (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of the <hi>Gentiles, Eph.</hi> 4.18.) Such are all men by nature, before God take acquaintance of them, reveal himſelf unto them; they are little better then (as the ſame Apoſtle faith of them, <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.12.) <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>without God in the world;</hi> having no acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:170076:83"/>with him, meer <hi>ſtrangers</hi> to him.</p>
                  <p>Which natural ſtrangeneſs (in the ſecond place) is habituated, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> confirmed, and increaſed more and more, by their continuing and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on in a courſe of actual ſin. Hereby they are daily eſtranged more and more; being (as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of his <hi>Coloſſians</hi> before their converſion, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.21.) <hi>Alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated, and enemies in their mindes by wicked works.</hi> Such is the condition of all wicked, yea, and of all carnal men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the grace of God meet with them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Applic.</hi> And being ſuch, let none reſt in ſuch a condition. A condition, how ſad? how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable? how miſerable? So men would account it to be whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſtranged from the <hi>Sun,</hi> the Fountain of light and heat. Such is God to the ſoul, the Fountain
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:170076:83"/>of all comfort and happineſs: To be eſtranged from him, did men but rightly apprehend what it is, they ſhould not need to be told that they are miſerable. In this eſtate, let not any ſoul of us ſit down, but ſtir up our ſelves to ſeek after God, to <hi>get acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> with him.</p>
                  <p>That is the thing which is here expreſſed. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>2</label> What men in this condition are to do, <hi>Acquaint themſelves with God.</hi> This is the leſſon which <hi>Eliphaz</hi> here holdeth forth unto <hi>Job.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with God, the nature of it opened.</note> And I wiſh it may make an impreſſion upon every of our hearts that hear it this day; which that it may the better do, I ſhall firſt by way of <hi>Doctrinal Explication</hi> open to you the phraſe, and the duty; and ſhew you what it is for a man to <hi>acquaint himſelf</hi> with God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Acquaint thy ſelf] Hasken</hi> (ſaith the Original,) A word, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Explic. </seg>
                     </label>
                     <pb n="136" facs="tcp:170076:84"/>which (as our <hi>New Annotators</hi> well obſerve upon the Text) is to be found in this conjugation (in <hi>Hiphil</hi>) but onely in two other places, beſides this, in the Scripture. The one is <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.3. where <hi>David</hi> ſpeaking of Gods <hi>omniſcience,</hi> his all-ſeeing providence, he ſaith, <hi>Thou art acquainted with all my ways. (Hiskaneta) Aſſueviſti,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> thou art <hi>accuſtomed, acquainted.</hi> Where the word imports the full and perfect knowledge which God had of <hi>Davids</hi> actions and words: So the next verſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains it [<hi>For there is not a word in my tongue, but thou knoweſt it altogether,</hi> Verſ. 4.] The other place is, <hi>Numb.</hi> 22.30. where <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſs arguing the caſe with her maſter, and repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him for ſmiting and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning her in that manner, for go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of her way, and falling
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:170076:84"/>down to ſave his life, ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of him, [<hi>Was I ever wont to do ſo unto thee?</hi>] Where the word (being the ſame) im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth a cuſtomary uſe and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice.</p>
                  <p>Now from theſe two places being put together, we may col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and take up what is the full comprehenſion of this word here in the Text, where <hi>Eliphaz</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſeth <hi>Job</hi> to <hi>acquaint</hi> himſelf with God. [<hi>Acquaint thy ſelf with him.</hi>] That is, firſt learn to <hi>know him,</hi> then accuſtom thy ſelf unto him, <hi>walk with him.</hi> In theſe two ſtandeth the acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance which one friend hath with another: Firſt in <hi>knowing,</hi> and then <hi>converſing</hi> each with other. And in theſe two ſtandeth a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians <hi>acquaintance</hi> with his God, in <hi>knowing</hi> of him, and <hi>walking</hi> with him.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt thing wherein this
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:170076:85"/>
                     <hi>acquaintance</hi> conſiſts, is <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</hi> A man can never be ſaid to be acquainted with a man whom he knoweth not: And ſo is it with God. That a man may be acquainted with him, he muſt <hi>know</hi> him; and that with a <hi>three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold knowledge;</hi> a knowledge of <hi>Speculation, Faith, Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. A knowledge of <hi>Specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> a general knowledge. To know that there is a God, and who that true God is; and what a one he is; what is his Nature, and what is his will. Such a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral knowledge one man muſt have of another, before he can be acquainted with him. And ſo is it with God: That a man may acquaint himſelf with him, he muſt have ſome knowledge of him; and that not onely a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed,</hi> but a <hi>diſtinct</hi> knowledge. Such is the knowledge which
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:170076:85"/>friends and acquaintance have one of another. They do not onely know each other by the <hi>face,</hi> but (as <hi>Iſaac</hi> knew his ſons) they know their voice, their demeanour and diſpoſition. And ſuch a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge muſt they have of God, who would be acquainted with him: Not onely a <hi>confuſed knowledge.</hi> Such was the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, of whom the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>They knew God, Rom.</hi> 1.21. This they did <hi>naturali jure, non familiari</hi> (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth,
<note place="margin">Tertul. <hi>De ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis, citat. per</hi> H. Grotium ad loc.</note>) onely in a <hi>natural</hi> way; they knew God by the light of nature, beholding him in his works; but this was not worth the name of <hi>knowledge.</hi> And therefore the ſame Pen elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where without any contradiction affirms the contrary, That they did not know God, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.5. <hi>The Gentiles which know not
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:170076:86"/>God.</hi> Though ſome of them knew him by his <hi>works,</hi> yet they did not know him, in and from his <hi>Word,</hi> by the Scriptures. Thus muſt they know God (in ſome meaſure) who would have any true acquaintance with him. They muſt know him to be ſuch a one, as he hath revealed himſelf in his Word; One God, Three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; a Great, a Glorious, a Wiſe, a Gracious, a Juſt, a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful, a Pure and Holy God; a God reconciling the world to himſelf, in and through his Son Jeſus Chriſt. Withal, they muſt know ſo much of his will, as may ſerve to regulate them in their duty towards him. Without this there can be no entercourſe, no acquaintance with him. This is requiſit, but not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> In the ſecond place then, there muſt be a <hi>knowledge of
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:170076:86"/>Faith</hi> Whereby a man appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends this God to be his God. A man is not ſaid to be acquainted with a man, unleſs he have ſome intereſt in him. Though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he know him never ſo well, yet unleſs there be ſome friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip betwixt them, he is not ſaid to be acquainted with him: So is it here. A man that is ſaid to be acquainted with God, he muſt apprehend him as <hi>his God,</hi> a <hi>God in Covenant.</hi> Such was <hi>Abrahams,</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> his, and <hi>Davids</hi> acquaintance with God. They looked upon him as their God. <hi>The Lord is my rock, and my fortreſs, and my deliverer; my God, my ſtrength, in whom I will truſt, &amp;c.</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt,) Pſal.</hi> 18.2. This is the <hi>knowledge of Faith.</hi> Concerning which, God maketh that promiſe to his Church under the Goſpel, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.34. <hi>They ſhall all know
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:170076:87"/>me from the leaſt of them to the greateſt of them.</hi>] They ſhall know me to be their God, a God reconciled to them, a God in Covenant with them. So he explains himſelf in the words following [<hi>For I will forgive their iniquity, and I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member their ſin no more.</hi>] Thus muſt they know God, who would be acquainted with him.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Yet further, to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleating and perfecting of this acquaintance, there is required alſo another kinde of knowledge, a <hi>knowledge of experience.</hi> This is ſometimes called by the name of <hi>acquaintance.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> As it is ſaid of <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.3. That he was <hi>a man acquainted with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Notus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritudine, i.e. Exper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitatem,</hi> Montan.</note> that is, one that had an experimental knowledge of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane infirmities. And ſuch a knowledge have they of God,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:170076:87"/>who are ſaid to be acquainted with him; they have an experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental knowledge of him, and of his divine perfections. Such was that knowledge of God, which holy <hi>Job</hi> ſaith he had at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to, after his afflictions, and Gods manifeſting himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him in that ſenſible manner, <hi>Job</hi> 42.5. <hi>I have heard of thee</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>by the hearing of the ear, but now mine eye ſeeth thee.] Job</hi> had before heard much of <hi>God,</hi> much of his power, wiſdom, mercy, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which he had received from his Anceſtors, having him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf had the benefit of a religious education; but now his <hi>eye ſaw him.</hi> God had now given him a ſenſible and experimental know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of himſelf, cauſing him to ſee and feel what he was to him. And ſuch a knowledge (in ſome meaſure) is requiſit to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleating
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:170076:88"/>of this <hi>acquaintance</hi> with God. It is not enough for men to <hi>hear</hi> of God, what a one he is; nor yet to <hi>beleeve,</hi> what they hear. But they muſt <hi>ſee</hi> God, have ſome experimental knowledge of him, ſpecially of his dealing with themſelves; of the exerciſe of his power, wiſdom, goodneſs, mercy for their good; and that ſpecially for the good of their ſouls; in working effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally upon their hearts, by his <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Spirit;</hi> in alluring and drawing them unto himſelf; in letting out himſelf to them; in giving them victory over their corruptions; comforting them with inward and ſpiritual conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations; hearing and anſwering their prayers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Here is the firſt thing, wherein this acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with God doth conſiſt, in <hi>knowing</hi> him, with a knowledge of <hi>ſpeculation, farth, experience.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="145" facs="tcp:170076:88"/>
                  <p>The ſecond thing is <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with him,</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                     <hi>walking with him.</hi> Such acquaintance had <hi>Enoch</hi> with his God, he <hi>walked with him, Gen.</hi> 5.22, 24. The like had <hi>Noah,</hi> of whom it is ſaid, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.9. <hi>And</hi> Noah <hi>walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with God.</hi>] Thus do they that are of acquaintance, walk toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. As <hi>David</hi> ſaith of his falſe friend, his <hi>acquaintance</hi> (as he calleth him) <hi>We took ſweet coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel together, and walked unto the houſe of God in company, Pſal.</hi> 55.13, 14. And by walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and converſing together, they come to increaſe their acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. So is it betwixt God and man. Man acquaints himſelf with God by <hi>walking with him;</hi> which conſiſts,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. In <hi>apprehending his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence</hi> in all places, taking notice of him as a witneſs to all his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, words, thoughts. This it is
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:170076:89"/>to <hi>walk before God;</hi> which the Lord requires <hi>Abraham</hi> to do, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1. And which <hi>David</hi> reſolved he would do, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.9. <hi>I will walk before the Lord in the Land of the living.</hi>] Liphni Jehovah,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>ad facies Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>before the face of</hi> Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah, in his preſence, always eying and beholding him. Thus did <hi>Moſes</hi> walk, of whom it is ſaid, <hi>That he ſaw him that was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible, Heb.</hi> 11.27. Setting God before him; as <hi>David</hi> ſaith of himſelf, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.8. <hi>I have ſet the Lord always before me, becauſe he is on my right hand, &amp;c.</hi>] Thus did he walk with God, living continually in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. To walk with God, is to <hi>obſerve his ſteps,</hi> his <hi>goings.</hi> Thus did the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> walk with God, through the Red Sea, and the Wilderneſs. <hi>They have
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:170076:89"/>ſeen thy goings, O God,</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt,) even the goings of my God, my King, in the Sanctuary, Pſal.</hi> 68.24. What <hi>goings?</hi> Why, his goings thorow the <hi>Sea,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ainſworth</hi> ad loc.</note> (ſo the <hi>Chaldee</hi> there para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſeth it, <hi>The houſe of</hi> Iſrael <hi>have ſeen the going of thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty upon the Sea,</hi>) and his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the <hi>Wilderneſs;</hi> ſo the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth verſe of that <hi>Pſalm</hi> may ſeem to explain it, [<hi>When thou wenteſt forth before thy people, when thou didſt march thorow the Wilderneſs.</hi>] There did they <hi>walk with God,</hi> beholding and obſerving him in the ſeveral tokens, and manifeſtations of his preſence among them; and in this way they came to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with him: And in the like way Chriſtians come by their acquaintance with him, by thus walking with him, by beholding and obſerving his goings, his
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:170076:90"/>ſpecial providences, the exerciſes of his power, mercy, and juſtice, upon themſelves and others: Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving his works, and diving in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. <hi>The works of the Lord are great</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt) ſought out of all them that have pleaſure therein,</hi> Pſal. 111.2.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. To walk with God, is to <hi>converſe with him.</hi> Thus do friends, walking together, they converſe each with other, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to, and hearing one another. And thus do Chriſtians acquaint themſelves with God, by having ſuch a <hi>converſe</hi> and <hi>communion</hi> with him; often ſpeaking to him, and hearing him ſpeak to them. Speaking to him in <hi>prayer</hi> and <hi>praiſe;</hi> hearing him ſpeak to them by his <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Spirit.</hi> Thus have the Saints of God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted themſelves with him, often ſpeaking to him. So did <hi>Daniel,</hi> whoſe conſtant courſe
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:170076:90"/>was to make his addreſſes unto God three times a day, <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.10. <hi>He kneeled upon his knees three times a day, and prayed, and gave thanks unto God, as he did aforetime.</hi>] And <hi>David</hi> the like <hi>[Evening and morning, and at noon, will I pray and cry aloud, &amp;c.] Pſal.</hi> 55.17. Such was his ſet and conſtant courſe of devotion; beſides many occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal addreſſes upon emergent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions. <hi>Seven times a day will I praiſe thee,</hi> (ſaith he,) that is, often, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.164. And thus ſpeaking to him, they were as ready to hear from him. <hi>I will hearken and hear what the Lord God will ſpeak,</hi> (ſaith the ſame <hi>Pſalmiſt,) Pſal.</hi> 85.8. And the like are all Chriſtians to do; thus acquaint themſelves with God, by thus <hi>converſing</hi> with him.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. And laſtly, walk with God, following him, walking in
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:170076:91"/>his ways. Thus do <hi>ſervants</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their <hi>maſters,</hi> walking in their way, the way which they have gone before them: And thus are Chriſtians to acquaint themſelves with <hi>God,</hi> by thus going along with him, following him, walking in his ways. That is one of the characters of <hi>Davids</hi> bleſſed man; He is one that <hi>walketh in the ways of his God, Pſal.</hi> 119.3. that is, in his Law (as the firſt verſe explaineth it.) This <hi>Law</hi> he receiveth from the mouth of his God. So <hi>Eliphaz</hi> exhorts <hi>Job</hi> to do in the verſe after the Text (which <hi>Junius</hi> looketh upon as exegetical to it) <hi>Receive, I pray thee, the Law from his mouth, and lay up his words in thine heart.</hi>] This doth the true Chriſtian. And having thus received the <hi>Law</hi> from God, being acquainted with his will, now he yeeldeth a willing
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:170076:91"/>and chearful obedience thereunto; <hi>ſerving God</hi> (as <hi>David</hi> adviſeth his ſon <hi>Solomon</hi> to do, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.9.) <hi>with a perfect heart, and with a willing minde.</hi> And thus doth he <hi>acquaint</hi> himſelf with God.</p>
                  <p>Now put theſe together, and you have (as I apprehend) the full import of this phraſe; what it is for a man to <hi>acquaint him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with God.</hi> The <hi>doctrinal part</hi> of which duty being thus opened, I ſhall now come to that which I principally aym at, <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which I ſhall direct onely in that way wherein here I meet with it in the Text, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Applic. </seg>
                     </label>
                     <note place="margin">The pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the duty perſwaded</note> a way of <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation. Acquaint now thy ſelf with God,</hi> ſaith <hi>Eliphaz</hi> to <hi>Job.</hi> And let me in the Name of God beſpeak every ſoul that heareth me this day, in the very ſame language, <hi>Now acquaint
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:170076:92"/>you your ſelves with him.</hi> A leſſon uſeful and needful for all ſorts of perſons. Amongſt whom we ſhall finde.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Some, and that the greateſt part, who have no acquaintance with God at all; they are meer ſtrangers to him. Such are all <hi>ignorant perſons,</hi> who have no knowledge of God. Such there were ſome amongſt the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> telleth them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.34. <hi>Some have not the knowledge of God, I ſpeak it to your ſhame.</hi>] The ſhame of the perſons guilty of it, and of thoſe that tolerated them amongſt them. And would to God the like might not be too truly ſaid of this, or any other Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that there are ſome amongſt them, who whileſt they bear the names of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> yet in reali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty they are little better then <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts;</hi> they have no knowledge
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:170076:92"/>of God, no true, ſound, diſtinct knowledge of him. Now as for ſuch, the evidence againſt them is but too clear, that they have no <hi>acquaintance</hi> with God. They are <hi>eſtranged from him through the ignorance that is in them, becauſe of the blindneſs of their mindes,</hi> (as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> in the place forenamed, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.18.)</p>
                  <p>And ſuch are all <hi>profane</hi> and irreligious perſons; of whom we may ſay as the ſame Apoſtle doth of the <hi>Heathen, Rom.</hi> 1.21. <hi>That when they knew God, they did not glorifie him as God.</hi> They do not walk according to the light which they have; though they know God with a kinde of ſpeculative knowledge, (it may be) yet they do not walk with him. They ſeldom or never think of him, <hi>God is not in all their thoughts</hi> (as <hi>David</hi> ſaith
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:170076:93"/>of the wicked man, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.4.) They do not apprehend his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence with them; they obſerve not his goings; <hi>they regard not the works of the Lord, nor the operation of his hands,</hi> (as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaith of them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 28.5.) They have no converſe with him; they are ſuch as <hi>call not upon God,</hi> (which the ſame <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> maketh a character of a wicked man, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 53.4.) They have no regard to follow God, to walk after him; they are ſuch as <hi>hate inſtruction, and caſt his words behinde them</hi> (as you have it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.17.) Saying un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, though not with their tongues, yet in their hearts (with thoſe in <hi>Job, Chap.</hi> 21.14.) <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from us, we deſire not the knowledge of thy ways.</hi>] Now as for ſuch, it well may nay it muſt be concluded againſt them, they are far from having any <hi>acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi>
                     <pb n="155" facs="tcp:170076:93"/>with God at all. And ſo this counſel is very proper for them. <hi>Now acquaint ye your ſelves with him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Others (in the ſecond place) they have ſome acquaintance with him; they know ſomewhat of him, and their deſire is to his Name, to walk with him, and approve themſelves unto him; but they are not acquainted with him as they ſhould be, and might be: Their acquaintance with him is but overly, not ſo <hi>intimate</hi> and <hi>familiar</hi> as ſome of the Saints of God have attained to, and themſelves might attain, were they not wanting to thoſe means of communion, which God is pleaſed to afford them. And who is there amongſt us, but may, and muſt acknowledge our ſelves to be of this number.</p>
                  <p>True, there is indeed a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of men (ſome whereof,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:170076:94"/>and too many are ſaid to be in this Nation at this day) who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to extraordinary familiarity and acquaintance with God, as if they did already know him, as they are, or ſhall be known of him. But I preſume there are none of them within the reach of my tongue at preſent: If there be, let me onely tell them, that had they more true acquaintance with God, they would think more meanly of themſelves, then now they do. When <hi>Job</hi> came to <hi>ſee God,</hi> then he <hi>abhors him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, Job</hi> 42.5, 6.</p>
                  <p>For you, looking upon you all in one of the former <hi>Claſſes,</hi> let me direct the <hi>Exhortation</hi> to all and every of you, <hi>Now, I pray you, acquaint your ſelves with God. You that have yet no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with him, ſeek it. You that have ſome acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with him, labor to confirm
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:170076:94"/>and increaſe it.</hi> To theſe two ſorts of perſons, I ſhall ſpeak ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally, and apart: Beginning with the firſt.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> You who have yet no <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with God;</hi> you have onely heard of him by the <hi>hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ear,</hi> but your <hi>eye hath not ſeen him;</hi> or if it hath, it hath been onely in the <hi>glaſs of the creature.</hi> Some general knowledge (it may be) you have of God, but no practical acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with him. To you be it ſpoken, and that with the like af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection that <hi>Eliphaz</hi> is here con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to ſpeak unto <hi>Job</hi> with; <hi>Now, I pray you, acquaint ye your ſelves with him.</hi> Do not you ſit down contented in this your eſtrangedneſs; but ſeek ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with God.</p>
                  <p>Which counſel, that it may take place with you, let me firſt awaken you by giving you to
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:170076:95"/>know, that if you be not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with God here, you ſhall never be acquainted with him hereafter. Mark it, (and the Lord ſet it on upon your ſpirits;) If you will not acquaint your ſelves with God here, you ſhall have no acquaintance with him hereafter. Now this latter (I preſume) there is none of you, but would be loth with. Loth would you be to hear that dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful doom paſs from the mouth of God, when you ſhall come to ſtand before his Tribunal, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from me ye curſed, I know you not.</hi> None of you but would then be willing and deſirous that God ſhould own you, and take acquaintance of you. And if ſo, then acquaint ye your ſelves with him now. <hi>No acquaintance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth, no acquaintance in Heaven.</hi> There is no room for <hi>ſtrangers.</hi> What the Prophet
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:170076:95"/>
                     <hi>Joel</hi> in the place forecited, ſaith of the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> upon Earth, is much more true of the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> in Heaven,
<note place="margin">Joel 3.17.</note> 
                     <hi>There ſhall no ſtrangers paſs through it,</hi> or yet enter into it. None but ſuch as have ſome ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with God.</p>
                  <p>Being thus awakned, now give way to ſome Arguments to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade with you, to ſeek after this <hi>acquaintance.</hi> For which I ſhall not need to go far. This verſe whereof the Text is part, furniſheth me with two, which may ſerve inſtead of many. In thus acquainting your ſelves with God, <hi>you ſhall have peace, and good ſhall thereby come unto you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu. </seg>1</label> 
                     <hi>Hereby you ſhall have peace.</hi> So ſome (and that not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs) look upon this paſſage in the Text, as an argument or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to induce <hi>Job</hi> to ſeek ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:170076:96"/>with God. <hi>Acquaint now thy ſelf with him, and be at peace.]</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Pacem habete,</hi> Have peace, or, ſo ſhalt thou be at peace. This ſhall a man get by this his acquainting himſelf with God; he ſhall have <hi>peace.</hi> A bleſſing which is not to be found in any other way. As for wicked and ungodly men, who by their ſinful ways and courſes, alienate and eſtrange themſelves from God, there is no <hi>peace</hi> for them. <hi>There is no peace to the wicked, ſaith my God,</hi> Iſa. 48.22. &amp; 57.21. Poſſibly they may (as too often they do) ſpeak peace to themſelves (as the <hi>falſe Prophets</hi> did to the <hi>Jews, Jer.</hi> 6.14. ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Peace, Peace, when there is no peace.</hi> No, being ſtrangers to God, they are ſtrangers to peace. This is a portion which God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves for thoſe that are of his acquaintance. <hi>The Lord will
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:170076:96"/>bleſs his people with peace,</hi> Pſal. 29. laſt. <hi>Thou wilt keep him in perfect peace, whoſe minde is ſtayed on thee</hi> (ſaith the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah, Chap.</hi> 26.3. In <hi>(perfect peace) peace, peace,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> (ſaith the Original,) that is,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> all manner of true and found peace. And ſuch peace ſhall they have who thus acquaint themſelves with God; they ſhall have <hi>Peace, peace; outward</hi> peace, <hi>inward</hi> peace.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Outward peace,</hi> outward tranquillity. This is that which <hi>Eliphaz</hi> elſewhere promiſeth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Job</hi> upon this very condition, of ſeeking unto God, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting himſelf with him. So doing (ſaith he) <hi>The Beaſts of the field ſhall be at peace with thee. And thou ſhalt know that thy Tabernacle ſhall be at peace,</hi> Job 5.23, 24. This is the next and ſureſt way even to outward peace, to be firſt at peace with
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:170076:97"/>God, to be acquainted with him. <hi>When a mans ways pleaſe the Lord</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Wiſeman) he maketh even his enemies to be at peace with him, Prov.</hi> 16.7. This God can do; and this ſo far forth as ſhall be good for them, he will do for thoſe who acquaint themſelves with him; command peace for them, <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward peace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. However (in the ſecond place) they ſhall have <hi>inward peace;</hi> Peace of Conſcience; which is their peculiar portion. As for wicked men, who are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtranged from God, they may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy outward peace, but inward peace they are ſtrangers to it. However their Conſciences being aſleep, they may be for a time at peace, feeling no inward diſquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet when God cometh to awaken them (which ſooner or later he will do) acquainting
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:170076:97"/>them with their condition, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them their eſtrangedneſs from him; now there can be no peace, nothing but horror and terror; a hell in their ſouls. <hi>There is no peace</hi> (no inward peace) <hi>to the wicked.</hi> But ſuch <hi>peace</hi> have they who are acquainted with God; having him to friend; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending him as their God, a God reconciled to them in Chriſt. <hi>Now being juſtified by faith, they have peace with God, Rom.</hi> 5.1. Inward peace, their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences being quieted with the true ſenſe, and apprehenſion of his love and favor to them. Thus they <hi>live</hi> in peace: And living in peace, they <hi>die</hi> in peace: <hi>Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into peace</hi> (as the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith of the Righteous man; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.2.) departing hence <hi>in peace, into peace;</hi> with peace in their ſouls, unto eternal peace and reſt with God in the Heavens.
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:170076:98"/>Here is the firſt of thoſe advant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages and benefits which the Text holdeth forth to thoſe who ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint themſelves with God. In ſo doing they ſhall have <hi>peace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu. </seg>2</label> And (ſecondly) <hi>thereby good ſhall come unto them.] Good.</hi> This it is that all men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire; <hi>Who will ſhew us any good?</hi> (ſay they) <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.6. Now this ſhall they attain who thus ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint themſelves with God. <hi>Good.</hi> A threefold good. The firſt of <hi>Honor;</hi> the ſecond of <hi>Pleaſure;</hi> the third of <hi>Profit.</hi> Theſe are the three chief goods, which the men of this world ſo earneſtly deſire, ſo eagerly hunt after. And behold all theſe meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together in a Chriſtians ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with his God. Here is true <hi>Honor, Pleaſure, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, Here is <hi>Honor:</hi> Upon
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:170076:98"/>this ground, mean men are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ambitious of getting ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with great perſonages; though they get nothing by it, nay it may be pay dear for it (as ſometimes they do) yet it is a credit, it is an <hi>honor</hi> to them. Now what an honor is it to be acquainted with the great God of Heaven? This was mans chief <hi>honor</hi> at the firſt, That he was of Gods acquaintance, having a near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er familiarity and communion with God, then the reſt of the Creatures; then was <hi>man in honor, Pſal.</hi> 49.12. And this is the higheſt honor that he is now capable of upon Earth, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to ſome degree of that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance. This was <hi>Abrahams</hi> honor, <hi>that he was called the Friend of God,</hi> Jam. 2.23. And this was <hi>Moſes</hi> his honor, that <hi>the Lord ſpake unto him face to face, as a man ſpeaketh unto his
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:170076:99"/>friend, Exod.</hi> 33.11. No honor like unto this, for man to know God, <hi>jure familiari</hi> (as he phraſeth it) in a familiar way, to be acquainted with him. To be acquainted with a <hi>Prince,</hi> ſo as to have his <hi>eye</hi> and his <hi>ear,</hi> to have free acceſs into his preſence upon all occaſions, to ſpeak fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly to him, to converſe with him, what an honor is it account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Such honor (and infinitely greater) have all Gods Saints, who have the like acquaintance with him.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Here is <hi>Pleaſure.</hi> Upon this ground again men oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times are willing to embrace ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with others. Their ſociety is pleaſant and delightful. And ſuch is this acquaintance with <hi>God;</hi> it affordeth ſweet pleaſure and delight unto the foul. So <hi>Eliphaz</hi> tells <hi>Job</hi> in the 26 verſe of this Chapter. <hi>Then
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:170076:99"/>thou ſhalt have thy delight in the Almighty.</hi>] Acquainting thy ſelf with him, thou ſhall not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ſuſtained by him, but thou ſhalt finde ſpecial delight, and ſingular pleaſure in him. So do the Saints in Heaven, ſtanding continually in the preſence of God, they finde an unſpeakable delight and complacency in him. <hi>In thy preſence is fulneſs of joy, at thy right hand there are pleaſures for evermore.] Pſal.</hi> 16.11. And the like in their meaſure do the Saints upon earth; in their converſe and communion with God, they finde a ſweet <hi>ſoul-complacency.</hi> Thence it is that communion with God is called ſometimes a <hi>delighting in God. Delight thy ſelf alſo in the Lord, Pſal.</hi> 37.4. That is, have communion with him; which who ſo have, they ſhall finde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in him. So runs the promiſe,
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:170076:100"/>which the Lord makes unto thoſe who conſcionably obſerve his <hi>Sabbaths,</hi> on thoſe days ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting themſelves with him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.13, 14. <hi>If thou turn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thy foot from the Sabbath, from doing thy pleaſure on my holy day, and call the Sabbath a delight,</hi> (taking delight in the duties and offices of the day,) <hi>&amp;c. Then ſhalt thou delight thy ſelf in the Lord;]</hi> Thou ſhalt finde in him ſuch abundant matter of delight, as ſhall miniſter a ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſatisfaction unto thy ſoul. To the ſame purpoſe is that other promiſe held forth by the ſame Prophet. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.2. <hi>Hearken diligently unto me,</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>and eat ye that which is good, and let your ſoul delight it ſelf in fatneſs.]</hi> Not in carnal, but in ſpiritual delights, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; which as far excel all ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual and earthly delights, as fat
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:170076:100"/>meat doth that which is lean. Theſe are the <hi>pleaſures</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Lord will ſatisfie thoſe that betake themſelves unto him, making him their refuge, putting their truſt under the ſhadow of his wings; <hi>They ſhall be abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly ſatisfied with the fatneſs of thy houſe, and thou ſhalt make them drink of the rivers of thy pleaſures,</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt,) Pſal.</hi> 37.7, 8. Such enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment will God give to thoſe who acquaint themſelves with him. <hi>Bleſſed is the man whom thou chuſeſt</hi> (ſaith the ſame <hi>Pſalmiſt,) and cauſeſt to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach unto thee, that he may dwell in thy courts; we ſhall be ſatisfied with the goodneſs of thy houſe, even of thy holy tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Pſal.</hi> 65.4. Such <hi>pleaſure</hi> is there in this acquaintance with God.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. And (thirdly) there is <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit</hi>
                     <pb n="170" facs="tcp:170076:101"/>in it. That is the Queſtion which thoſe wicked ones in the Chapter before the Text (<hi>Job</hi> 21.25.) propound to themſelves and others. <hi>What is the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty that we ſhould ſerve him; and what profit ſhould we have, if we pray unto him?</hi>] And ſo thoſe <hi>Hypocrites</hi> in <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachi</hi> the like. <hi>What profit is it</hi> (ſay they) <hi>that we have kept his Ordinances, and that we have walked mournfully before the Lord of hoſts? Mal.</hi> 3.14. And thus carnal men are ready to think of this the Chriſtians acquainting himſelf with God, that there is nothing to be got by it, that there is no profit in it. But herein how far are they miſtaken? Never was any man a looſer by his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with God. Great is the gain, great is the profit here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. <hi>Godlineſs with contentment, is great gain,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.6. <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:170076:101"/>is profitable for all things, having the promiſe of this life, and that which is to come,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. Such is the profit of this <hi>acquaintance.</hi> Great good ſhall come thereby; and that both <hi>Temporal, Spiritual,</hi> and <hi>Eternal.</hi> Of the former of theſe <hi>Eliphaz</hi> maketh large promiſes unto <hi>Job</hi> in the ſequel of this Chapter; where explaining what <hi>good</hi> ſhould come unto him upon his acquainting himſelf with God, among other things he tells him, <hi>Then ſhalt thou lay up gold as duſt, and the gold of Ophir, as the ſtones of the brooks,</hi> Verſ. 24. And in the Verſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, <hi>Then ſhalt thou have plenty of ſilver,</hi> Verſ. 25. <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>ſilver,</hi> theſe are the Worlds <hi>goods,</hi> moſt commonly (how properly I will not ſay) called by that name. And theſe he maketh promiſe of, and that in abundance
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:170076:102"/>to <hi>Job.</hi> Which promiſe God will make good, ſo far as ſhall be good for thoſe who perform this condition. Friends do not uſe to deny their intimate ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, any common favor that they can do for them. Such are theſe bleſſings, the bleſſings of <hi>Gods left hand,</hi> (as <hi>Solomon</hi> deſcribeth them, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.16.) they are but common favors. And being ſuch, God will not withhold them from thoſe that acquaint themſelves with him, ſo far as they may be expedient for them. <hi>No good thing will he withhold from them that walk uprightly, Pſal.</hi> 84.11. However, he will not be wanting to them in thoſe two other and better kinds of good things, <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Eternal. The Lord will give grace, and glory,</hi> (ſaith the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part of that Verſe.) <hi>Grace</hi> here, <hi>glory</hi> hereafter. So true is
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:170076:102"/>it, what <hi>Eliphaz</hi> here tells <hi>Job,</hi> that acquainting himſelf with God, <hi>thereby good ſhould come unto him;</hi> as <hi>Honor</hi> and <hi>Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi> ſo <hi>Profit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And Arguments (methinks) I ſhould need to uſe no more, to induce you to hearken to this counſel. Any one of theſe will prevail with men to embrace ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with men. O let all of them prevail with us, to embrace acquaintance with God.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>But will God be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with us, poor, vile,
<note place="margin">Encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gements to the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</note> worthleſs creatures that we are, how ſhall we dare to take ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance of the great God?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> In way of anſwer to this, let me propound two or three <hi>encouragements,</hi> which may ſerve as further induce ments to bring in poor ſinners unto God.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Conſider, that he diſdaineth
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:170076:103"/>not the acquaintance of the leaſt of men, or of the greateſt of ſinners. This Princes and great men for the moſt part do. <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaking of ſome, who had him in deriſion in his adverſity, he ſaith they were ſuch, as <hi>whoſe fathers he would have diſdained to have ſet with the dogs of his flock, Job</hi> 30.1. So low they were in condition, and ſo far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath him in the time of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, that he would have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to have had any thing to do with them, to employ them in the meaneſt office about him. But it is otherwiſe with the <hi>God</hi> of Heaven; whoſe Majeſty, though it be ſo great, that it is a kinde of <hi>humbling</hi> to him <hi>to behold the things that are in Heaven, and in the Earth</hi> (as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> phraſeth it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 113.6.) Yet he vouchſafeth graciouſly to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint himſelf with the meaneſt
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:170076:103"/>of thoſe that ſhall ſeek acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with him. Such was the condeſcenſion of the <hi>Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> that it diſdained not that near acquaintance with the <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane;</hi> to take the nature of man into a perſonal union with it ſelf. And ſuch was the condeſcenſion of our bleſſed Saviour upon earth, that he diſdained not the acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of thoſe, who upon a vulgar account were the vileſt of men, even of <hi>Publicans</hi> and <hi>Sinners, Matth.</hi> 9.11. And ſuch is the gracious condeſcenſion of the moſt high God; that he diſdain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not acquaintance with any of thoſe who deſire acquaintance with him.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Nay (ſecondly) he <hi>offers and tenders this acquaintance</hi> to them. This do not great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages ordinarily to their infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors. Their acquaintance muſt be ſought, and it may be bought;
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:170076:104"/>they do not uſe to offer it. But this doth the Lord our God. He offers his acquaintance to poor ſinners; he <hi>puts forth the hand</hi> to them, (as <hi>Abſalom</hi> is ſaid to have done to thoſe who came nigh to tender their duty, and do him obeyſance, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.5.) he inviteth them to come in, that they may have acquaintance with him. This he doth in the offers and tenders of grace held forth in the Goſpel, which he ſends forth his <hi>Miniſters</hi> to declare and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh. Even as that great <hi>Feast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker</hi> in the Goſpel, who ſent forth his ſervants into the <hi>high ways,</hi> to <hi>invite</hi> and <hi>compel</hi> thoſe whom they found, to come in to his <hi>Supper,</hi> to eat and drink with him, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.23. So doth God ſend forth his Miniſters with the like commiſſion, to <hi>invite</hi> and <hi>compel,</hi> by <hi>Goſpel promiſes,</hi> and <hi>legal threatnings,</hi> all ſorts of
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:170076:104"/>poor ſinners to come in, that they may have communion with him.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. And this he doth (in the third place) out of his <hi>meer grace and favor,</hi> onely for their good, their benefit; not for any gain or advantage to himſelf. Upon that account it was that <hi>Abſalom</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered himſelf in that over-famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar manner, to thoſe that came nigh him. His deſign was to make ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of their acquaintance. But this cannot God expect from man. <hi>Can a man be profitable unto God?</hi> (ſaith <hi>Eliphaz</hi> in the beginning of this Chapter, Verſe 2.) No, God is not, cannot be a gainer by our acquaintance. That he offers it, ſeeketh it, it is for our good, our benefit; that we may be made happy and bleſſed in it, and by it. O then let not this grace of God be in vain to any of us, but accept we this ſo graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:170076:105"/>an offer; acquainting our ſelves with him.</p>
                  <p>And this do we <hi>forthwith. Now acquaint thy ſelf with him</hi> (ſaith <hi>Eliphaz</hi> to <hi>Job</hi> here.) And let me in this ſenſe ſay the ſame words to every ſoul among you, that is yet eſtranged from God. <hi>Now acquaint thou thy ſelf with God.</hi> Now, now, whileſt God is pleaſed to offer and tender this acquaintance; which how long he will do, who knoweth? He that offers it to day, it may be will refuſe it to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. If the <hi>door of grace</hi> be once ſhut, then they who <hi>ſtand with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out</hi> may <hi>knock,</hi> as it were taking acquaintance of God, ſaying, <hi>Lord, Lord, open to us,</hi> but they ſhall receive no other anſwer, then that which there followeth, <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.25. <hi>I know not whence you are.</hi> And therefore, <hi>As the Holy Ghoſt ſaith, To day if ye will
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:170076:105"/>hear his voice, harden not your hearts, (Heb.</hi> 3.7, 8.) <hi>Now,</hi> whileſt the day of grace laſteth, <hi>now</hi> come in. <hi>Now is the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted time, now is the day of ſalvation,</hi> (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2.) Now, whileſt the <hi>golden ſcepter</hi> is held forth; whileſt the Goſpel is preached unto you. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore eſtrange your ſelves from God no longer; but now come in, and <hi>acquaint your ſelves with him.</hi> Do it forthwith.</p>
                  <p>Knowing, that <hi>acquaintance is not ordinarily got of a ſudden.</hi> The word in the Text (as I ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you) it imports a <hi>cuſtomary practiſe.</hi> And ſuch is <hi>acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> it is not commonly attained but in continuance of time, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed and repeated acts of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce. And ſo is it with this <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with God.</hi> True it is, ſometimes God cometh in, in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary ways appearing unto
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:170076:106"/>men, after a ſort, as he did to <hi>Moſes</hi> in the <hi>Buſh, (Exod.</hi> 3.4.) throughly acquainting himſelf with them at the firſt meeting, as he did with <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 9. But this is not his ordinary courſe. Acquaintance, as with men, ſo with God, in an ordinary way, is not the work of an hour, or a day. And therefore forthwith ſet upon it.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Quest. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>But how ſhall we go about it? In what way ſhall we come to obtain this bleſſed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> Now, would to God that all that are here before the Lord this day,
<note place="margin">Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for getting acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with God.</note> were but come thus far, thus to ſeek after God, how they might acquaint themſelves with him? As for you who are unfeignedly deſirous of it, take theſe few, and plain directions.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. In order hereunto (as I told you in opening the nature of the
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:170076:106"/>duty) the firſt thing to be done, is to <hi>know him. And thou</hi> Solomon, <hi>my ſon, know thou the God of thy Fathers, and ſerve him,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.9. No knowledge, no acquaintance. And therefore, that you may have acquaintance with God, let it be your care firſt to know him. To which end, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult not onely the Book of the <hi>Creature,</hi> but alſo of the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:</hi> That you may know him not onely by his <hi>works,</hi> but by his <hi>word.</hi> Know him to be ſuch a one as he hath there revealed himſelf to be. What he is in <hi>himſelf,</hi> what he is in his <hi>Son,</hi> what are his <hi>properties,</hi> what his <hi>will.</hi> This is the <hi>key</hi> that muſt let you into this acquaintance, <hi>The key of knowledge.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Then (ſecondly) lay aſide ſuch things as may obſtruct and hinder this acquaintance. What thoſe are, the Lord himſelf will
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:170076:107"/>tell you, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Waſh ye, make ye clean, put away the evil of your doings from before mine eyes, &amp;c. Then come and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with me.</hi>] Mark it; there is no parlying, no reaſoning with God, no acquaintance to be had with him, unleſs all known ſins be laid aſide. A <hi>rebel</hi> that would have any acquaintance with his <hi>Prince,</hi> muſt firſt throw down his arms, lay aſide the weapons of his rebellion. And ſo muſt they who would have any acquaintance with God, they muſt put away ſin, all ſin. Sin being Gods enemy, ſo long as we hold a correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency and acquaintance with it, we can have no acquaintance with God. This is that which <hi>Joſhua</hi> tells the people, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24.19. <hi>Ye cannot ſerve the Lord, for he is an holy God, he is a jealous God, &amp;c.</hi>] A jealous husband cannot endure a corrival in his love, that
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:170076:107"/>his wife ſhould communicate her ſelf, between him and a ſtranger. No more can God, that thoſe who pretend to love him, and to deſire intimate acquaintance with him, ſhould embrace the boſom of any ſinful, inordinate luſt. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore either reſolve to break off ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with the one, or never ſeek acquaintance with the other. <hi>If I regard iniquity in my heart, the Lord will not hear my prayer</hi> (ſaith <hi>David,) Pſal.</hi> 66.18. He will not own me, he will have no acquaintance with me. No, <hi>God is of purer eyes then to behold evil, and cannot look on iniquity;</hi> ſo the Prophet <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bakkuk</hi> deſcribeth him, <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.13. And therefore, you that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to acquaint your ſelves with him, give a Bill of Divorce to all ſinful luſts, putting them away out of your hearts and lives, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving never more to have any
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:170076:108"/>acquaintance with them, to give any entertainment to them.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Then (in the third place) being thus prepared for this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, now make uſe of a <hi>Mediator.</hi> This courſe do men take, who deſire to acquaint themſelves with the <hi>Prince,</hi> or ſome great perſonage, being themſelves ſtrangers, much more if they have been enemies to him; they make uſe of ſome ſpecial favorite to make way for them, to procure acceſs into his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and to ingratiate them with him, that ſo they may get acquaintance with him. Now ſuch is the condition of all men by nature, in reference to <hi>God;</hi> they are not onely <hi>ſtrangers</hi> to him, but <hi>enemies; (Alienated, and enemies in your mindes by wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed works,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> of his <hi>Coloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi> before converſion, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.21.) And being ſuch, that they
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:170076:108"/>may get acquaintance with God, their onely way is, to make uſe of a <hi>Mediator.</hi> What <hi>Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor?</hi> Why, as there is but <hi>one God,</hi> ſo there is <hi>but one Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor betwixt God and Man, the Man Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. He is the great favorit of Heaven, of intimate acquaintance with God the Father, having lyen in his boſom from all eternity. Make uſe of him then; by Faith, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hold upon him, and ſo come unto God by him, preſenting your ſelves unto God in his <hi>Name,</hi> through his <hi>Merit,</hi> and <hi>Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> craving acceptance in, and thorow him.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. And thus coming unto God, then (in the fourth place) in humble-wiſe <hi>take acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of him.</hi> Now in all humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity <hi>challenge thy relations,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him <hi>thy God,</hi> and <hi>thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> Now look upon him as a
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:170076:109"/>God reconciled to thee, in and thorow Jeſus Chriſt, and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed in him. <hi>This is my wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloved Son, in whom I am wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed,</hi> (ſaith the voice from Heaven, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.17.) <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Wel-pleaſed with him, and with all whom he beholdeth in him. Here is now the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans entrance into this bleſſed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance.</p>
                  <p>Which being thus happily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> (now to ſpeak to the ſecond ſort of perſons) labor to <hi>confirm and increaſe it.</hi> Had <hi>Eliphaz</hi> here looked upon <hi>Job,</hi> as in truth he was, as a man that had ſome acquaintance with God already, yet might he have ſaid unto him what here he doth, <hi>acquaint thy ſelf with him;</hi> do it more and more. And the like let me ſay unto you, who have already tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row grace obtained ſome ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with God, <hi>Acquaint
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:170076:109"/>you your ſelves with him.</hi> Still labor for a further degree of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance: Alar, as for that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, which as yet you have, it is comparatively but flender and overly; labor for a more intimate, a more familiar acquaintance with your God.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>But how,</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>or in what way ſhall that be attained?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> A uſeful Queſtion. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> Take the anſwer to it in theſe four or five directions.
<note place="margin">Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, By a <hi>further enquiry after him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>A ſerious and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent meditation of him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, <hi>A diligent obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fourthly, <hi>A frequent inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fiftly, <hi>A cloſe and conſtant walking before him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe are the cheif ſteps of this Ladder, by which a Chriſtian
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:170076:110"/>may aſcend to an intimate ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with God. Herein let me deſire you to go along with me; as with your <hi>attentions</hi> now, ſo with your <hi>practice</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The firſt ſtep is, <hi>A fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inquiry after God. Then ſhall we know</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>if we follow on to know the Lord, Hoſ.</hi> 6.3. Alas, Chriſtians! that which the beſt of us know of God already, is but the leaſt part of what we are ignorant of, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>We know but in part</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> of his <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> and of himſelf,) 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.9, 12. Such is the knowledge of God, which the moſt illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Saints here attain unto. It is but defective, and imperfect. As for thoſe who think <hi>they know any thing</hi> (are moſt highly opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nionated of their own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.) <hi>Paul</hi> will tell them, <hi>They
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:170076:110"/>know nothing yet as they ought to know,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.2. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let it be our endeavor to <hi>fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low on to know the Lord;</hi> Still en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring further after him; after his <hi>Nature, Attributes, Will.</hi> This is that which <hi>Paul</hi> beggeth in the behalf of his <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> that they might <hi>increaſe in the knowledge of God, Col.</hi> 1.10. And this let every of us labor after. In thus following on to know the Lord, <hi>we ſhall know,</hi> we ſhall come to have more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with him.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Thus enquiring af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, be ſerious and frequent in our <hi>meditation of him.</hi> In this way <hi>David</hi> came by his acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with God; <hi>by being ſtill with him. When I awake</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I am ſtill with thee, Pſal.</hi> 139.18. Still with him, by way of Meditation and Contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of him, thinking of him. Thus
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:170076:111"/>was he with God at his lying down, in the night ſeaſon. <hi>He remembred him upon his bed, and meditated on him in the night watches</hi> (as himſelf ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,) <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.6. And thus was he with him at his riſing up. As in the night, ſo in the morning. Still he was with God. And ſo let it be with us, as many as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire acquaintance with God. <hi>Be we ſtill with him.</hi> Meditating of his <hi>Attributes,</hi> his <hi>Works,</hi> his <hi>Word,</hi> his <hi>Teſtimonies,</hi> his <hi>Law.</hi> It is one of the characters which <hi>David</hi> giveth of his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed man; <hi>His delight is in the Law of the Lord, and therein doth he meditate day and night, Pſal.</hi> 1.2. In this way a man cometh to be acquainted with a thing; by often looking upon it, often thinking of it. In this way acquaint we our ſelves with God.</p>
                  <pb n="191" facs="tcp:170076:111"/>
                  <p>Thirdly, Thus contemplating of him, be we alſo diligent in <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving</hi> him; Eying and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his <hi>goings,</hi> his <hi>providences;</hi> ſpecially his <hi>ſpecial providences;</hi> the out-breakings of his power, wiſdom, juſtice, mercy, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and that as upon others, ſo eſpecially upon our <hi>ſelves.</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve <hi>what God is to us;</hi> how good, how gracious; how he preventeth us with his mercies; how he ſteppeth into us in our ſtraits; how he comforteth us in our tribulations; how he <hi>maketh his goodneſs to paſs before us.</hi> And here, make we ſpecial ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of his ſecret and <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual in-comes</hi> to our ſouls; how he meeteth us in our approaches unto him; what anſwers he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns to our prayers; what enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment he affordeth us in his houſe; how he <hi>ſatisfieth our ſouls with marrow and fatneſs</hi>
                     <pb n="192" facs="tcp:170076:112"/>(as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.5.) How he <hi>kiſſeth us with the kiſſes of his mouth,</hi> (as the <hi>Spouſe</hi> phraſeth it, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.1.) What intimations of his peculiar love he affords us; how he work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth upon our hearts by his Word and Spirit. Theſe are the goings of the Lord, in, and upon the hearts of his people; which thoſe, who would have intimate ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with him, muſt make diligent obſervation of.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, In the fourth place, thus obſerving of him, <hi>have frequent intercourſe with him.</hi> In this way men come to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted, by having frequent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terviews, often meeting together, to ſee one another, to diſcourſe and converſe each with other. And in this way acquaint we our ſelves with God: Often coming into his preſence; often meeting with him. Meeting him in <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick,</hi>
                     <pb n="193" facs="tcp:170076:112"/>in his <hi>Ordinances,</hi> in his publick worſhip. Here it was that <hi>David</hi> got much of his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with God, by meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him in his <hi>ſanctuary. I have ſeen thee, O God, in the ſanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary, Pſal.</hi> 63.2. And here meet we with him; converſing with him by <hi>ſpeaking</hi> to him, and <hi>hearing</hi> and <hi>receiving</hi> from him. Speaking to him by <hi>Prayer;</hi> hearing from him in his <hi>Word;</hi> receiving from him the pledges of his love in the <hi>Sacraments.</hi> And thus meeting him in publick, do the like in <hi>private.</hi> Publick in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terviews without private enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, will never breed intimate acquaintance. And therefore as we meet God <hi>in his houſe,</hi> ſo meet him in our own houſes; as we meet him in the <hi>Church,</hi> ſo meet him in the Cloſet; keeping conſtant courſe of private devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; going unto God at ſet
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:170076:113"/>times, ſo upon all emergent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, to make ſuit for mercies we want; to return praiſes for mercies received. No better way to get acquaintance with God, then thus frequently to <hi>pour forth the heart before him,</hi> (as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſpeaketh,) <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62.8. to pour it out by way of <hi>Confeſſion, Petition, Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fifthly, To theſe adde in the laſt place, <hi>a cloſe and conſtant walking with, and before him.</hi> A conſtant adhering, and cloſe cleaving unto him. This is that which <hi>Moſes</hi> preſſeth upon the people, <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.20. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13.4. <hi>You ſhall ſerve him, and cleave unto him.</hi> And this do we; Cleaving to him in <hi>affection,</hi> and <hi>converſation.</hi> In <hi>affection,</hi> fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, loving him, truſting in him, depending upon him. In <hi>converſation,</hi> walking before him
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:170076:113"/>as in his preſence, endeavoring to approve our ſelves unto him in our whole courſe, not willingly doing ought that might offend him, that might cauſe him to turn away his face, and eſtrange himſelf from us; but <hi>ſerving him without fear, in holineſs and righteouſneſs before him, all the days of our lives.</hi> Thus <hi>walking with God,</hi> we ſhall daily grow up in our <hi>acquaintance</hi> with him.</p>
                  <p>Which that it may not be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Caution. </seg>
                     </label> for the regulating of us herein, take but this one <hi>Caveat.</hi> In acquainting our ſelves with God, ſee that we <hi>keep our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</hi> This do inferiors uſe to do, who acquaint themſelves with ſuperiors; ſuch as are far above them in place and eſtate, they keep their diſtance, not being too familiar with them. The like ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve we in this our acquainting
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:170076:114"/>ourſelves with God. He being in Heaven, we upon Earth; he an infinite Majeſty inhabiting that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that <hi>unapproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, unacceſſible light,</hi> (as the Apoſtle deſcribeth him, and it, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6, 16.) And we poor worms, creeping upon this Mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil of Earth, in acquainting our ſelves with him, <hi>keep our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance;</hi> be not too familiar with him; whether it be in our <hi>enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> after him, or <hi>obſerving</hi> of him, or <hi>converſing</hi> with him, or <hi>walking</hi> before him.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. In our <hi>enquiring</hi> after him, keep our diſtance. This is the charge which the Lord willeth <hi>Moſes</hi> to give unto the people, when himſelf was to appear up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Mount <hi>Sina,</hi> Exod. 19.12. <hi>Thou ſhalt ſet bounds unto the people round about, ſaying, Take heed unto your ſelves, that ye go not up into the Mount, or
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:170076:114"/>touch the border thereof.</hi> And again, Verſ. 21. <hi>Go down, charge the people, leſt they break tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row unto the Lord to gaze, &amp;c.</hi> And this charge let us obſerve. Take we heed of coming too near unto God in our enquiries after him; of being too familiar with him. This I look upon, as a weakneſs in <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf. God having been familiar with him, <hi>Speaking unto him face to face, as a man ſpeaketh to his friend,</hi> (as it is expreſſed, <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.11.) that is, more plainly and familiar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then with others; hereupon <hi>Moſes</hi> takes the boldneſs to deſire to <hi>ſee his face,</hi> his <hi>glory; And he ſaid, I beſeech thee ſhew me thy glory,</hi> Verſ. 18. <hi>i. e.</hi> A full manifeſtation of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, which, as the Lord there tells him, was more then he, or any other mortal Creature was capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of, [<hi>Thou canſt not ſee my
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:170076:115"/>face; for there ſhall no man ſee me, and live,</hi> Verſ. 20.] Take we heed of the like preſumption. Is it ſo, that God hath acquainted himſelf in a more familiar way with us, then with others: take heed of being over-bold with him; of advancing too far in our enquiries concerning him, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his <hi>Nature, Counſels, Will, Works.</hi> For his <hi>Nature,</hi> let it be enough that God <hi>maketh his goodneſs to paſs before us,</hi> and that he giveth us a ſight of his <hi>back-parts.</hi> For his <hi>Counſels,</hi> dive we not too far into them; but ſtanding afar off, admire and adore what we cannot comprehend, crying out with the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>O the depth! Rom.</hi> 11.33. For his <hi>Will,</hi> content we our ſelves with that part of it which is revealed: Remembring, that <hi>ſecret things belong unto the Lord, but revealed things to us,
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:170076:115"/>and to our children, Deut.</hi> 29. laſt. Let us not dare to look into <hi>Gods Ark,</hi> to pry into the Cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net of his ſecret Counſel. Here remember we that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.3. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Not to be wiſe above that we ought to be wiſe; but to be wiſe unto ſobriety.</hi> And for his <hi>works,</hi> be not too inquiſitive after a reaſon of them. Let it be enough to us, <hi>The Lord hath done it,</hi> in whom there can be no improvidence or unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Thus keep our diſtance, come not too near unto God, in enquiring too far after him.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. And ſo (ſecondly) in our <hi>obſerving of him,</hi> keep our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, come not too near. It is no good manners for a ſervant to follow his maſter ſo cloſe, as to tread upon his heels. Thus do they follow <hi>God,</hi> who pretending to a more then ordinary acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:170076:116"/>with him, will take upon them to make a ſudden and peremptory conſtruction, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of all his <hi>Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> of his proceedings and deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with themſelves, and others. Collecting and concluding (that which the <hi>Preacher</hi> ſaith, <hi>No man can know, Eccleſ.</hi> 9.1.) <hi>Love or hatred, from that which is before them</hi> Concluding Gods <hi>love</hi> to themſelves, from his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and proſpering of them in outward things; his <hi>hatred</hi> of others, from his correcting and afflicting of them. This the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> however by many croſs-providences he was temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to it, yet upon ſecond and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious thoughts he durſt not do it, as he tells us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.15. <hi>If I ſay I will ſpeak thus,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>behold I ſhould offend againſt the generation of thy children.</hi>] Should he judge of men by Gods
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:170076:116"/>outward diſpenſations, and deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with them, he might eaſily wrong both him and them, in cenſuring godly men to be Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, becauſe it may be they are moſt acquainted with affliction. That was the miſtake (as of the reſt of <hi>Jobs</hi> friends, ſo) of <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaz</hi> here, who looked upon <hi>Job,</hi> as a man that had no <hi>acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> with God, becauſe the hand of God lay ſo heavy upon him. Take we heed of making the like conſtructions of Gods providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial diſpenſations. This is to be too familiar with God, to follow him too cloſe.</p>
                  <p>And ſo is it, when men ſhall make <hi>Providence</hi> their <hi>guide</hi> to follow, their <hi>Compaſs</hi> to <hi>ſtear</hi> by, their <hi>Rule</hi> to <hi>walk</hi> by; not expecting any further manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods will and pleaſure from his Word.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Keep our diſtance in <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:170076:117"/>with him.</hi> Thus do <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriors</hi> in the civil intercourſe, which they have with their <hi>ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors;</hi> though acquainted with them, yet they obſerve their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, not being too familiar with them; but ſhewing ſuch reſpects to them in their language and deportment, as their eminency requireth. And the like do we in our <hi>ſpiritual entercourſe</hi> and <hi>communion</hi> with God; in ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him, in hearing or receiving from him, take heed of being too familiar with him. So was that proud <hi>Phariſee;</hi> when he came into the <hi>Temple</hi> in that bold and conſident way; inſtead of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing his ſins, preſenting unto God a catalogue of his good works, [<hi>God I thank thee, I am not as other men, &amp;c. I faſt twice in the week, I give tithes of all that I poſſeſs,] Luke</hi> 18.11, 12. Thus doth he (as it were)
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:170076:117"/>take and challenge acquaintance with God, upon the account of his own demerits. Far be the like preſumption from every of us. Coming unto God, be it in <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick,</hi> or in <hi>private,</hi> come we with all humility and reverence. So cometh the poor <hi>Publican</hi> there in the verſe following. He obſerves his diſtance, <hi>he ſtandeth afar off</hi> (in ſome remote part of the firſt Court of the Temple,) <hi>not ſo much as lifting up his eyes to Heaven</hi> (ſo taking unto himſelf ſhame and confuſion of face,) but <hi>ſmiting upon his breſt,</hi> (in token of true and hearty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition) he ſaith, <hi>God be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to me a ſinner.</hi>] And ſo coming, the ſequel tells us, that <hi>he went away juſtified, rather then the other,</hi>] Acquitted and accepted. Do we deſire to finde the like reſpects from God; let all our addreſſes unto him be in
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:170076:118"/>the like manner, with an humble and awful reverence of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty. Here take heed of being too familiar with him. That is the caveat which the <hi>Preacher</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth to thoſe who make any pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick addreſs unto God, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Keep thy foot, when thou goeſt into the houſe of God;</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luding (as ſome conceived) to that of God to <hi>Moſes,</hi> when appearing to him in the buſh, he bids him, <hi>Put off thy ſhooes from thy feet, Exod.</hi> 3.5. in token of reverence; or (as others) to that ordinary cuſtom of the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> who were to <hi>waſh their feet,</hi> when they came to officiate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, <hi>Exod.</hi> 30.19, 21. Thus he requireth all who come before the Lord to offer up any ſpiritual ſacrifice unto him, to <hi>take heed to their feet,</hi> as to their outward <hi>geſtures,</hi> ſo ſpecially to their inward <hi>affections. Keep
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:170076:118"/>thy foot, when thou goeſt into the houſe of God, and be more ready to hear, then to offer the ſacrifice of fools. Be not raſh with thy mouth, and let not thine heart be haſty to utter any thing before God; for God is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and thou art upon Earth, therefore let thy words be few.</hi> Thus come we before God in <hi>publick; reverencing his ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary,</hi> (as the Lord requires, <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.30. &amp; 26.2.) And thus come we to him in <hi>private;</hi> with all due reverence and obei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance: Remembring that they who would <hi>ſerve God accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly,</hi> muſt ſerve him <hi>with reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and godly fear, Heb.</hi> 12.28. In both, ſo take acquaintance of God, as yet obſerving and keeping our diſtance.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. And laſtly, In our <hi>walking before him;</hi> See that we ſo walk <hi>before him,</hi> as that yet we walk
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:170076:119"/>
                     <hi>after him.</hi> So <hi>Moſes</hi> requires the people to do, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.4. <hi>Ye ſhall walk after the Lord your God.</hi>] So do ſervants walk <hi>after</hi> their maſters, and mean perſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages <hi>after</hi> their ſuperiors. And ſo do we <hi>after our God.</hi> Not run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning before him. So did thoſe falſe <hi>Prophets</hi> of old, of whom the Lord complains, that they <hi>ran before they were ſent, Jere.</hi> 23.21. And ſo do they, who thruſt themſelves into any publick ſervices and employments, which God hath not called them to. They herein go before God. For us, herein know we, and keep we our diſtance, following after him. If the Lord be God, follow him, (ſaith <hi>Eliah</hi> to the people,) 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.21. Deſire to ſee God go before us in all our ways, taking our directions from him. Not, preſenting unto him ſuch ſervices as we think ſitting; but
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:170076:119"/>ſuch as himſelf requireth. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, walking humbly with him. He hath ſhewed thee, O man, what is good; and what doth the Lord require from thee, but to do juſtly, and to love mercy, and to walk humbly with thy God? (ſaith the Prophet, <hi>Micah</hi> 6.8.) Thus walk we with him, humbly; humbling our ſelves to walk with him (as the <hi>Hebrew</hi> hath it.) So walking with him here, we ſhall live with him hereafter; enjoying a bleſſed communion with him unto all eternity. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
